<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Antichrist in spirit unmasked: or, Quakerism a great delusion. Being an answer to a pamphlet lately published and dispersed in and about Deptford in Kent, intituled The Christianity of the people commonly called Quakers. Which they say is asserted against the unjust charge of their being no Christians, upon several questions relating to those matters wherein their Christian belief is questioned. By which pamphlet they would perswade the world that the Quakers are Christians. In which answer you have their deceit detected, their pretended faith examined and proved a counterfeit / by Edw. Paye ...</title>
            <author>Paye, Edw. (Edward)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 139 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09693</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 9863765</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P883</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09863765</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09863765</idno>
            <idno type="VID">192303</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09693)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 192303)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; 1641-1700 ; 2913:12a, 1365:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Antichrist in spirit unmasked: or, Quakerism a great delusion. Being an answer to a pamphlet lately published and dispersed in and about Deptford in Kent, intituled The Christianity of the people commonly called Quakers. Which they say is asserted against the unjust charge of their being no Christians, upon several questions relating to those matters wherein their Christian belief is questioned. By which pamphlet they would perswade the world that the Quakers are Christians. In which answer you have their deceit detected, their pretended faith examined and proved a counterfeit / by Edw. Paye ...</title>
                  <author>Paye, Edw. (Edward)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>87 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year, 1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproductions of originals in the Trinity College Library, Cambridge University (1365:2) and Haverford College Library (2913:12a).</note>
                  <note>Item at 2913:12a with: Railings and slanders detected: or The folly and Heresies of the Quakers further exposed. London : [s.n.], printed in the year, 1692.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christianity of the people commonly called Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:192303:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:192303:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Antichriſt in Spirit unmasked: OR, <hi>Quakeriſm a great Deluſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being an Anſwer to a Pamphlet lately publiſhed and diſperſed in and about <hi>Deptford</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> intituled, <hi>The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity of the People commonly called</hi> QUAKERS.</p>
            <p>Which they ſay is aſſerted againſt the unjuſt Charge of their being no Chriſtians, upon ſeveral Queſtions relating to thoſe Matters wherein their Chriſtian Belief is queſtioned.</p>
            <p>By which Pamphlet they would perſwade the World that the QUAKERS are Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>In which ANSWER you have their Deceit de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected, their pretended Faith examined, and proved a Counterfeit.</p>
            <q>And no marvel; for Satan himſelf is transformed into an Angel of Light.
<bibl>2 Cor. 11. 14.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>If that Light that is in them be Darkneſs, how great is that Darkneſs?
<bibl>Mat. 6. 23.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>They are of thoſe that rebel againſt the Light, they know not the Ways thereof, nor abide in the Paths thereof.
<bibl>Job 24. 13.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>And for this cauſe ſhall God ſend them ſtrong Deluſions, that they ſhould believe a Lie.
<bibl>2 Theſſ. 2. 11.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>Edw. Paye,</hi> a Servant of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1692.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:192303:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:192303:2"/>
            <head>A Commendatory Epiſtle to the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Impartial Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> art here preſented with an Examination of the pretended Faith profeſſed by the <hi>Quakers,</hi> lately publiſhed and diſperſed in <hi>Deptford.</hi> It appeared to the World with a fair Aſpect, and the Ignorant and Eaſy were ready to take their Words, that they ſo believed: But the Author, to unfold their Riddles, hath made uſe of their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruing Books, to get at their Meanings; and it fully appears to be nothing ſo believed by them, as pretended in their Pamphlet. We believe neither Ambition, Self-Intereſt or Prejudice, moved the Author to this Work; but purely, the Honour of God, Defence of Truth, and Good of Souls. We alſo hope and believe, that he hath been careful truly to cite the <hi>Quakers</hi> own Authors; and we believe, if any Error therein be, as to Page or the like, it may be juſtly imputed as an over-ſight. <hi>Reader,</hi> thou art foretold by our Lord, <hi>That in the laſt Days many falſe Prophets ſhall ariſe, and deceive ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:192303:3"/>
And the Apoſtle informs of ſome, that <hi>with feigned Words, and fair Speeches, ſhall deceive the Hearts of the Simple:</hi> And of others, <hi>That ſhall privily bring in damnable Hereſies, even denying the Lord that bought them,</hi> &amp;c. and that <hi>many ſhall follow their pernicious Ways,</hi> &amp;c. So that, as was ſaid in another Caſe, we may ſay in this, <hi>Is there not a Cauſe?</hi> The Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures, which this Generation of Men contemn and vilify, as will appear in this Diſcourſe, go very nigh to us; we always having had, and hope ever ſhall have a vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable eſteem for them.</p>
            <p>And thus we commend the enſuing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the Judgment of the unbiaſſed Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, hoping Error may be detected, and the Truth preſerved from Seducers, who would introduce their corrupt Notions in the room thereof: And we ſhall reſt with theſe Deſires, true Friends to all that love Truth and Peace,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>Hen. Loader.</item>
                     <item>William Allcot.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:192303:3"/>
            <head>Quakeriſm a great Deluſion.</head>
            <p>THE Subſtance of their pretended Faith may be reduced into theſe ſix general Heads.</p>
            <p>I. In the firſt and laſt Articles profeſſed, they ſay, they believe, according to holy Scripture-Teſtimony, in the Trinity, or thoſe three Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Witneſſes that bear Record in Heaven, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that they believe and own the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, contained in the Books of the Old and New Teſtament, and to be given by Divine Inſpiration, and to contain all matters of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Teſtimony, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> neceſſary to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved and practiſed in order to Salvation and Peace with God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>II. They ſay their Belief is, that in the Unity of the God head there is Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, being thoſe three Divine Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes that bear Record in Heaven, the Father, the Word, and the holy Spirit, and that theſe three are one, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>III. They profeſs to believe the Divinity and Humanity of Chriſt, the Eternal Son of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that he is the one Mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and Man, the Man Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:192303:4"/>IV. They profeſs to believe and expect Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Sins, Juſtification, Redemption and Salvation, through the Sufferings, Death and Blood of Chriſt, and not by their own Works, Righteouſneſs or Merits—this is profeſſed in their third and fourth Articles ſpecified in their Pamphlet.</p>
            <p>V. They profeſs to believe and own the Divine Offices of Chriſt, as King, Prieſt and Prophet, over his own Church and People.</p>
            <p>VI. They evade and deny Baptiſm in Water, and the Supper of the Lord inſtituted in Bread and Wine, to be now in force, as ſtanding Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances in the Church of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>They ſay nothing of thoſe two great Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Bodies from the Graves of the Earth, and the eternal Judgment; tho they are not ignorant that their Faith hath been queſtioned herein.</p>
            <p>Before I proceed to examine their pretended Faith profeſſed in their Pamphlet, I ſhall take notice of its Title; it is called, <hi>The Chriſtianity of the People commonly called Quakers;</hi> and could we take them at their words, their Profeſſion looks like good and Orthodox. But as the Apoſtle ſaith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 13. there were <hi>deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Workers, transforming themſelves into the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of Chriſt;</hi> uſing feigned words and fair Speeches, was the old way of deceiving the Hearts of the ſimple. As our Enemies at Sea, either to defend themſelves from our Stroak,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:192303:4"/>
or to draw us into their Snare, will put up the Engliſh Flag: So the Quakers ſee it neceſſary upon this occaſion, to make a very plauſible Profeſſion. The gilded Pill is not ſo irkſome to the Palat; but if we are cautions in taking Money, and if a Piece be fair and large, yet if the Metal be ſuſpicious, we bring it to the Touch-ſtone.</p>
            <p>1. Chriſtianity is a very high, holy and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Profeſſion, which hath cauſed many to lay claim to it without a juſt Title, who will needs have the Name, tho ſtrangers to the Nature of Chriſtianity: many have no better a Title to this Name, than their being born in a Nation called a Chriſtian Nation. Others depend upon Morality alone, and bleſs God they are not ſo bad as ſome other Men. Chriſtianity is to lay hold upon Chriſt by a true and Evangelical Faith, in his Death, Sufferings and Merits, for Redemption and Juſtification; to believe him in all his Offices, and obey him in all his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances. Chriſtians are Diſciples or Scholars of Chriſt. <hi>Acts 11. 26. The Diſciples were firſt called Chriſtians at</hi> Antioch. A true Goſpel-Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, from a real and Evangelical Faith, attended with a pious Life; for Morality is included where there is true Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>2. Quakeriſm, with reſpect to the Name, is not derived from a Perſon ſo called, but from a Geſture uſed much amongſt them formerly in their Meetings, as was manifeſt by what was alledged againſt them by the <hi>Weſtmoreland</hi> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioners, <hi>viz.</hi> That their Practice did exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:192303:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:192303:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:192303:6"/>
ſavour of Saucery, becauſe of the Swel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, Quakings, Roarings and Foamings that were amongſt them at their Meetings. And in the Quakers Anſwer to this Petition, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny not ſwelling, foaming and quaking: See their Book, <hi>p.</hi> 35. But they deny Saucery and Blaſphemy: They juſtify quaking and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, as being uſed by the Saints of old, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 21. <hi>Jer.</hi> 33. 9. <hi>Acts</hi> 9. 6. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 12. 18. Theſe Texts are urged by <hi>Ja. Nailor,</hi> p. 16, 17. of his Book called, <hi>The Power and Glory of the Lord ſhining out of the North:</hi> He takes pains to prove their Name, and juſtify their Practice; for, ſaith he, ſearch the Scriptures, and holy Men of God do witneſs Quaking and Trembling: This is true, and the ſame may be ſaid of wicked Men and Devils, <hi>Acts</hi> 24. 25. <hi>James</hi> 2. 19. and <hi>Luke</hi> 9. 39. we read of him that was poſſeſſed, that he foamed, when the Diabolical Spirit did tear him. I ſhall ſay no more of their Name, it is of their own procuring and defending, tho no diſcriminating Character of Chriſtianity or Saintſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly;</hi> As to their Profeſſion, for ought that ever I could gather from their own Tongues or Pens, is a Labyrinth of Confuſion, or a great heap of Contradictions, tending to the Subverſion both of the Foundation and Fabrick of Chriſtianity; being a Compound of Hereſies, having Affinity with the Sadduces, as Mr. <hi>Brown</hi> notes, in the diſcovery of the Leaven of the Sadduces hid among the Quakers, <hi>p.</hi> 5. which Sect was divided into two Branches, <hi>Epicures</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:192303:6"/>
and <hi>Stoicks;</hi> theſe encounter'd St. <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 17. 18. calling him <hi>Spermologus,</hi> which our Tranſlation renders <hi>a Babler,</hi> becauſe he preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Jeſus and the Reſurrection; and with the Hereſy of <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus,</hi> 1 Tim. 2. 18. who ſaid, <hi>the Reſurrection was paſt already;</hi> and had overthrown the Faith of ſome: and they have Affinity with the <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> who ſay, that Chriſt did not take Fleſh really, but in a Figure; ſo have the Quakers ſaid, as will appear. See <hi>Saul</hi>'s Errand to <hi>Damaſcus;</hi> compare <hi>Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, Hereſ.</hi> 26. And they have Affinity with <hi>Seleucus,</hi> a great Heretick, who denied the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity of Chriſt, and Water-Baptiſm; he lived in the time of <hi>Theodoſius Magnus.</hi> See <hi>Auguſt. lib. de Hereſ.</hi> Both which Errors are main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the Quakers, repugnant to the holy Scriptures Teſtimony.</p>
            <p>Again, They have Affinity with the Papiſts in their Maſter-veins of Popery: for as the Papiſts do introduce all their vain Conceits by this Maxim, That the Church cannot err: So the Quakers uſher in their Dreams, that they are perfect, and ſo cannot err. And as the Papiſts make the Writings of their General Councils equal with the Scriptures, ſo do the Quakers their lying Pamphlets; nay, prefer them above the Scriptures, as will appear. And they have Affinity with the Muggletoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, who utter their execrable Imprecations, Curſes and Sentences againſt their Oppoſites. And I muſt leave them in this Deluge of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and Hereſy, and proceed to examine
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:192303:7"/>
their Pamplet in its reſpective parts.</p>
            <p>1. In the firſt Head, being part of the firſt and laſt Articles profeſſed in their Pamphlet, they profeſs to believe holy Scripture-Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, and that the holy Scriptures, contained in the Books of the Old and New Teſtament, do contain all matters of Doctrine and Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony neceſſary to be believed and practiſed in order to Salvation and Peace with God; and that they deſire to live in the Faith, Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg and Practice of them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in all things appertaining to Life and Godlineſs. Holy Scripture being given by Divine Inſpiration, is <hi>profitable for Doctrine, Correction, Inſtruction, that the Man of God may be perfect, throughly furniſhed unto every good Work; able to make the Man of God wiſe unto Salvation, through Faith in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed there is a preſent occaſion for this plauſible-Profeſſion; for the Promoters of it have now ſet up a Meeting in <hi>Deptford,</hi> a place where their corrupt Notions have had but little foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and it is alſo a place where the Word of God hath for many Years been faithfully and powerfully preached; ſo that except they appear in Sheeps Clothing, they cannot draw Diſciples after them. It is ſaid of the Oracles of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, that they were made to look with two Faces, that they may the better effect their Deceits. It is not eaſy to conceive the many Meanings and Reſerves that lie couched in this Paragraph. But not to trace them into all their equivocal Reſerves, I conceive the beſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:192303:7"/>
way to underſtand the Quakers Sentiments about the Scriptures, is to have recourſe to their own Conſtruing Books.</p>
            <p>And I ſhall begin with <hi>Humphrey Smith,</hi> a forward Aſſerter of Quakeriſm: ſee his Book called, <hi>A true and everlaſting Rule,</hi> p. 29. he affirmeth in the Face of Men and Devils, <q>That there are no other Rules, Ways or Means by which Men ſhall ever come to walk with God, but by that which is manifeſt of God in him; and that it is ſufficient to guide in all the Ways of God without Scripture, or any other outward Rule.</q> Doth not this tend to make null what is before profeſſed? If that in <hi>Humphrey Smith</hi> be a ſure Guide, and his Book be a true and everlaſting Rule, how then are the Scriptures neceſſary? and wherein are they profitable for Doctrine, Inſtruction, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſince all things neceſſary may be taught without them?</p>
            <p>See alſo <hi>James Nailor</hi>'s Anſwer to the Jews, <hi>p.</hi> 4, 22, 25. <q>It's Blaſphemy for any to ſay the Letter is the Word of God, it is the Devil that contends for the Scriptures to be the Word of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> Here you have the Sentence of one of their great Prophets paſſed againſt the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>George Whitehead</hi> being asked, Whether they eſteem their Speakings to be of as great Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity as any Chapter in the Bible? He affirms, in his Apology, <hi>p. 49. That which is ſpoken by the Spirit of Truth in any, is of as great Authority as the Scripture, yea, and greater.</hi> What can ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:192303:8"/>
more clear, than that the <hi>Quakers</hi> Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are of as great, if not greater, (But why do I mince it?) ay, and greater Authority than the Scriptures? Let us add to this <hi>James Parnell</hi>'s Teſtimony, <hi>Shield of the Truth,</hi> p. 19. he alſo that ſaith, <hi>The Letter is the Rule and Guide of the People of God, is without, feeding upon Husks, and is ignorant of the true Light,</hi> &amp;c. By this Man's Verdict, the Scriptures are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned as Husks, or a falſe Light. Could ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Papiſt, or Atheiſt, more plainly oppoſe the Holy Scriptures? But ſince we want no Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to detect theſe Impoſtors, let us add a few more from their own Pens; ſee <hi>James Naylor</hi>'s <hi>Light of Chriſt,</hi> p. 19. <q>God is at liberty to ſpeak to his People by the Scriptures, if he pleaſe; and where they are given by Inſpiration, doth ſo; and he is alſo at liberty to ſpeak by any other created thing, as to <hi>Balaam</hi> by his Aſs.</q> I think I do not wrong them, if I infer from hence, that the Sons of Men may as well expect Teachings and Rebukes from an Aſs, as from the Scriptures, one hath as much Authority eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentially in it ſelf as the other; one hath in it ſelf as much Authority to guide, teach and inſtruct the Sons of Men, as the other; neither can teach Men, except God immediately inſpire them. You ſee by this, how theſe divinely-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired Men eſteem the Scriptures of Truth. See the joint Conſent of two of their chief Guides, <hi>Fox</hi> and <hi>Hubberthorne, Truth's Defence,</hi> p. 101. they ſay, <q>The Scriptures are no ſtanding Rule, and that it is dangerous for the ignorant People
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:192303:8"/>
to read them. Surely if they had bin brought up at St. <hi>Omers,</hi> they could not more poſitively have denied the Scriptures.</q> I hope the Reader will remember how theſe chief Guides amongſt the <hi>Quakers,</hi> agree with the Account in the Pamph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, ſee <hi>pag.</hi> 29. of Mr. <hi>Hicks</hi>'s <hi>Dialogue;</hi> 
               <q>One <hi>Thomas Holbrow,</hi> a great Zealot among the <hi>Quakers,</hi> as appeared by the Journey he took to deliver a Meſſage to one <hi>James Nobs,</hi> which he ſaid was immediately delivered to him from the Lord: But it ſo unhappily fell out, that <hi>James Nobs</hi> was forty Miles off when the ſaid <hi>Holbrow</hi> came to the Meeting; ſo that either the God that ſent <hi>Holbrow</hi> did not know <hi>Nobs,</hi> or elſe at leaſt was ignorant that he was gone from Home at that time, for he delivered the Meſſage to a wrong Perſon. This I have had te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified to me as a Truth by ſeveral in thoſe Parts. And in <hi>p. 27. Dial.</hi> But this is not what I intend, for afterwards <hi>Tho. Holbrow</hi> having ſome Reaſonings with <hi>James Nobs</hi> and his Wife, the ſaid <hi>Nobs</hi> urging many Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures againſt <hi>Holbrow;</hi> the ſaid <hi>Holbrow</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, <hi>What doſt thou tell me of Scriptures, which are no better to me than an old Almanack?</hi>
               </q> It is like, when <hi>Humphrey Smith</hi>'s <hi>True and Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Rule</hi> came in date, the Scriptures became no better than an old Almanack. The brevity of this ſhort Diſcourſe, will not admit me to draw the proper Inferences that would naturally flow from theſe Premiſes. Theſe are the Men that in their Pamphlet profeſs ſo high an Eſteem for Holy Scriptures. See <hi>James Pernell</hi>'s Book,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:192303:9"/>
               <hi>Chriſt Exalted,</hi> p. 4. <q>Chriſt is the Word, the Scripture is not; Chriſt is the Light, the Scripture is not; he is the Ruler, Guide, Teacher and Judg, the Scripture is not.</q> And thus he goes on, like a Cloud carried with the Wind. It is like, from the Title of his Book, he concludes from theſe Expreſſions, to exalt Chriſt; when indeed he caſts the greateſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon him; Chriſt ſaith, <hi>If any Man love me, he will keep my Word.</hi> What are the written Words of Chriſt, but Scripture? But more of this hereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dialog.</hi> 1. p. 24, 25. <q>
                  <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> is it then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous and honeſt for you to deny the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to be a Rule to others, tho at the ſame time, but by miſinterpreting it, you make it a Rule to your ſelves? Are you not aſhamed of this Deceit and ſelf-condemning Partiality?</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Quaker,</hi> Thou miſtakeſt us, we own not the Scriptures to be our Rule; and whereas thou haſt ſaid many things to render us guilty of condemning this in others, whilſt we our ſelves ſeemingly allow it to be ſo, which is but thy own Imagination; for when we make uſe of Scripture, it is only to quiet and ſtop their Clamours that plead for it as their Rule; but for us, had the Scriptures never been, we could have known what is therein contained.</q> I hope the Reader by this may perceive the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why the <hi>Quakers</hi> talk ſo much of Scripture in their Paper; obſerve, <hi>We own not the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; we ſeemingly allow it; but our End in this, is only to ſtop their Clamours that plead for it as their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:192303:9"/>
Rule.</hi> You ſee here the condeſcending Spirits of theſe Men, that they ſhould allow the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to others, ay, and make uſe of them to pleaſe others, and yet not own them as a Rule themſelves; but their End is to ſtop clamorous Tongues. But here is their great diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, the old Birds will not be caught with this Chaff, their ſeeming Allowances will not paſs for Chriſtian Principles; <q>When the Mask is taken off, as <hi>Weſtfield</hi> ſaid concerning Chriſt, you are not able to bear what we have to hold forth concerning him; ſhould we deliver what we hold concerning Jeſus Chriſt, we ſhould be ſtoned in the Streets.</q> 
               <hi>Weſtfield</hi> a Quaker, <hi>Dialog.</hi> p. 74, 75. And indeed ſhould they hold forth in their Teaching what hath dropt from the Pens and Mouths of their chief Guides at ſome times, they would draw but few in their right Minds into their clouded Deluſions.</p>
            <p>But obſerve what is before ſaid; <hi>As for us, had the Scriptures never been, we could have known what is therein contained:</hi> This I have alſo heard from their own Mouths. Then I deſire the Quakers to reſolve me in theſe two Queſtions; it is ſaid, <hi>John 21. 25. And there are alſo many other things that Jeſus did, the which if they ſhould be written every one, I ſuppoſe that even the World it ſelf could not contain the Books,</hi> &amp;c. Again, it is ſaid, <hi>John</hi> 8. 6, -8. when the Woman taken in Adultery was brought to Chriſt, that he <hi>ſtooped down, and wrote with his Finger on the ground,</hi> &amp;c. Now let the Quakers reſolve me by their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:192303:10"/>
Inſpirations, what thoſe things were that Jeſus did that are not written, and what were the Contents of that Writing on the Ground? or elſe let their proud Boaſtings of immediate Inſpiration, be condemned to perpetual ſilence, and Shame cover their Faces. And waiting for their Reſolve herein, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to examine the Suffrage of great <hi>George Fox,</hi> who thinks he doth the buſineſs effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; ſee his <hi>Difference of Miniſters,</hi> pag. 1. he diſcants upon <hi>John</hi> 1. 1. <q>Thus <hi>John</hi> did not ſay, the Declaration was the Word, but ſaith in his Declaration, the Word was God; and he that ſaith the Letter is the Word, is a Deceiver, and errs.</q> The Argument lies here; becauſe Chriſt is called the Word, the Scriptures muſt not be ſo called. <hi>John</hi> ſaid, the Word was God; then the Scriptures cannot be the Word, except they be God alſo. It ſeems by the Quakers Logick, they are Deceivers and err; that call the Scriptures the Word of God, the Reaſon is, becauſe Chriſt is ſo called. Why then let us ſee 1 <hi>Cor. 10. 4. Iſrael</hi> in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <hi>drank of that ſpiritual Rock that followed them; and that Rock was Chriſt:</hi> But are there not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Rocks properly ſo called? A Rock is a hard congealed heap of Stone. <hi>John</hi> 10. 1. God is called an Husbandman; but are not Men that plow and till the Ground properly ſo called? Chriſt is called a Vine, a Door, and a Shepherd; but are there not other Vines, Doors and Shepherds in a proper ſenſe? Sure the Quakers will grant there are, Chriſt is
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:192303:10"/>
called the Light of the World, and yet <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 14. he tells his Diſciples, they <hi>were the Lights of the World.</hi> We own Chriſt to be called the Word of God, and yet the Scripture is ſo called in a true and proper ſenſe. Chriſt is the only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son of God, <hi>Joh. 3. 16. 1 Cor. 8. 6. Eph.</hi> 4. 5. But he hath more words than one, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. 4. a Scripture from <hi>Deut.</hi> 8. 3. to oppoſe the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil's, Aſſault; <hi>Man lives not by Bread alone, but by every Word that proceedeth out of the Mouth of God.</hi> Prov. 30. 5. <hi>Every Word of God is pure. Jer.</hi> 23. 36. the Complaint is, The falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets had <hi>perverted the Words of the Living God.</hi> A great Evil, and too common in this day. But would the Quakers have the Word always to intend Chriſt? <hi>Mark 4. 19. The Cares of this World, and the Deceitfulneſs of Riches, and the Luſts of other things entring in, choke the Word.</hi> Will the Quakers ſay, theſe things entring in, choked Chriſt? Surely no. By all this the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious Reader will ſee the Endeavours that have been uſed by the Quakers to explode the holy Scriptures, not only to rob them of their Nature, Uſe, Power and Efficacy, but alſo of their very Name. But let all Chriſtians learn to prize them, and carefully improve them, and be thankful to Divine Providence, by which they have been preſerved through all Times, and againſt all Tyrants. <hi>Pſal. 19. 7, 8. David</hi> ſets forth the worth of them: <hi>The Law of the Lord is perfect, converting the Soul; the Teſtimony of the Lord is ſure, making wiſe the ſimple. The Statutes of the Lord are right, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:192303:11"/>
the Heart: the Commandments of the Lord are pure, enlightning the Eyes.</hi> 2 Tim. 3. 15, 16. <hi>They are able to make wiſe to Salvation.</hi> Soul, thou needeſt not fear miſcarrying, if thou makeſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the holy Scriptures the Rule of thy Faith, and Guide of thy Life. This ſhort Treatiſe will not admit me to enlarge: I ſhall leave this ſhort Scheme, by which the Reader may judg what an Eſteem the Quakers have for holy Scriptures they ſo much pretend to in their Pamphlet.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">The Names they give the holy Scriptures.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Scriptures no ſtanding Rule, it is dangerous for the ignorant to read them.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>No better than an old Alma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nack, neither Rule, Guide, Light nor Teacher.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A dead carnal Letter.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>They are Precepts and Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of Men.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Paper, Iak and Writing.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Letter without, Swine feeding on Husks.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Obedience to Scriptures is the Harlot's Child.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>You may as well expect God to teach or rebuke by any other Creature as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, as he did <hi>Balaam</hi> by his Aſs.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">The Names they give their own lying Pamphlets.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A true and everlaſting Rule.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Royal Law and Covenant of God.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Love to the Loſt.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>News out of the North, written from the Mouth of God.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The pure Language of the Spirit.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A Salutation to the Seed of God.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Lip of Truth.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Spirit of Truth.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A Trumpet from the Lord, ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out of <hi>Zion.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A true Prophecy of the mighty Day of the Lord.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Word of the Lord, and a Word from the Lord, <hi>p.</hi> 13. of the Mighty Day of the Lord.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Bluſn O Heavens, and tremble O Earth, at the Pride and Ignorance of theſe Impoſtors!</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:192303:11"/>I ſhall add but two or three Paſſages more concerning their Contempt of the Scriptures: ſee <hi>Tho. Lawſon, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntaught Teacher,</hi> p. 6, 7, 8. <q>The Scriptures are not a Rule whereby Men may know the Will of Chriſt.</q> And in <hi>Pag.</hi> 2, and 3. of the ſame Book, he denies that the Miniſters of Chriſt, endowed with the Spirit of Chriſt, ought to miniſter or preach from Scripture. Add to this what is ſaid in <hi>Cloud of Witneſſes,</hi> a Book of theirs, <hi>p.</hi> 1, 3, 4. <q>But the Prieſts of <hi>England,</hi> the blind Guides—they do teach the People, and ſay, Hearken to the Word of the Lord, as it is in ſuch a Chapter and Verſe.</q> Now is it not a ſign that the Quakers are untaught Teachers indeed: but let the Word of God be true, and theſe Men Liars. Did not our Lord make uſe of the Scriptures in teaching, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21. 42. ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Did ye never read in the Scriptures, The Stone that was ſet at naught by you Builders?</hi> and <hi>Mat. 22. 29. Ye do err, not knowing the Scriptures.</hi> Surely they will not deny Chriſt to have the Spirit; and he proves the Reſurrection of the Dead by Scripture, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3. 6. Surely <hi>Peter</hi> had the Spirit, yet he proves Chriſt to be the great Prophet, <hi>Acts</hi> 3. 22. from <hi>Deut.</hi> 18. 15. And will they deny <hi>Philip</hi> to be endowed with the Holy Ghoſt? <hi>Acts</hi> 8. 35. he preacheth Jeſus to the Eunuch from <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. And <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 2, 11. <hi>Paul</hi> reaſoned and preached out of the Scriptures, and the <hi>Bereans</hi> ſearched the Scriptures, to try whether <hi>Paul</hi>'s Doctrine was true or not. The Reader may ſee from hence,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:192303:12"/>
with what an open Face theſe deluded Impoſtors will aſſert apparent Falſhoods. From all this it appears, the Quakers are great Enemies to, and Contemners of holy Scriptures, and that what they ſay in their Pamphlet is a great Falſhood.</p>
            <p>II. I proceed to examine the other part of their firſt Article profeſſed in their Paper.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Article.</hi> Our Belief is, <q>That in the Unity of the Godhead, there is Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, being thoſe three Divine Witneſſes that bear Record in Heaven, the Father, the Word, and the holy Spirit.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This Profeſſion looks like good and Orthodox Chriſtianity; but yet when it comes to be weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it will be found wanting. I ſhall only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine what Heaven this is the Quakers intend: not in the glorious Heavens above, beyond the Clouds and ſtarry Heavens, no by no means; it's ridiculous to ſpeak of an imagined God beyond the Stars: it is the Heaven within thee where theſe three Divine Witneſſes are: you will hear their ſevere Rebukes by and by, if you will have any other Heaven to be meant as their Reſidence. See <hi>James Parnell</hi>'s Book, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan's Deſign diſcovered,</hi> p. 19, 25. he affirmeth, <q>They that confeſs not Chriſt to be come in their Fleſh, are the Antichriſt;</q> and alſo affirmeth, <q>That by preaching of Chriſt in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the Devil gets his Work done on Earth.</q> Pray, what is fairly to be inferred from hence? why the Heaven they intend is no where elſe, but within their Mortal Corrupt Bodies; or
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:192303:12"/>
elſe Chriſt is not one of thoſe three Divine Witneſſes they ſpeak of in the Paper: for they will allow of no other Chriſt, but what is in every Man. And ſee further, <hi>Tho. Lawſon</hi> in his Book againſt <hi>William Jeffery,</hi> calls him, <q>Thou Image-maker, thou Cockatrice, hatching Eggs, Vulters Eye, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> becauſe <hi>William Jeffery</hi> had ſaid, that Chriſt was aſcended into Heaven with that Body that was raiſed from the Dead.</q> And they intend no other Heaven than what is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them, and thus they muſt be underſtood in their Pamphlet: for ſee <hi>Lawſon</hi>'s Book, <hi>p.</hi> 9, and 19. they ſay that they have eternal Life now really in Poſſeſſion. But would you have it more plain, that the Quakers Heaven is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them, take a Teſtimony out of <hi>Edward Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough</hi>'s Works, <hi>Pag.</hi> 9, 149. a chief Guide a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, therefore you may take his word for it: <q>We ſay, he that was ſlain upon the Croſs, is the very Chriſt of God, and the very Chriſt of God is in us.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Tho <hi>Lucock</hi> being ask'd ſeveral times before many Witneſſes, where that Heaven was that Chriſt did aſcend into, and now was in? he anſwered, clapping his Hands upon his Breaſt, <hi>Within me, Within me.</hi> I ſhall not trouble you much more in diſcovering to you the Quakers Heaven, and what they intend by it. <hi>G. Fox</hi> in his <hi>Great Myſtery,</hi> p. 16. writes thus; <q>Thou art deceived, who ſaith, Chriſt is diſtinct from the Saints. Can any Man eat the Fleſh of Chriſt, if his Fleſh be not in them? Can you call him Chriſt in Man, if the Man be not
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:192303:13"/>
there? <hi>George Whitehead, Dip. Plong.</hi> Chriſt without us is not Scripture-Language; but the <hi>Anthropomorphites,</hi> and <hi>Muggletonians,</hi> and <hi>Socinians,</hi> ſaith he, tell us of a Perſonal Chriſt, and that the Man Jeſus our Lord hath a place in Heaven remote from the Earth.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Let this ſerve to ſatisfy the impartial Reader, that the Quakers believe the Heaven they intend, to be within them: and they are but Hereticks that believe in a Chriſt in any other Heaven remote, or at a diſtance from them; for it is plain, that they deny Chriſt to be a diſtinct Perſon without them. And in like manner all the three Divine Witneſſes they ſpeak of, that bear Record in Heaven, are within them alſo; for the Light within them is really and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly Chriſt, and Chriſt is God: But this will further appear under the next Head. But let all Chriſtians believe that Jeſus Chriſt is at the Right-hand of the Father in the glorious Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens above. However the Quakers do endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with their falſe Gloſſes to abuſe the World, and bethrone Chriſt. We own and believe thoſe Scriptures in their true and proper ſenſe: 2 <hi>Cor. 13. 5. Know ye not that Chriſt is in you, except ye be Reprobates?</hi> 1 Cor. 6. 19. <hi>Ye are the Temples of God; and Chriſt in you the Hope of Glory,</hi> &amp;c. And it is alſo true, that the Saints are ſaid to be in Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor. 5. 17. If any Man be in Chriſt, he is,</hi> or <hi>let him be, a new Creature. And he that dwelleth in Love, dwelleth in God, and he in him.</hi> How often doth <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeak of the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in Chriſt Jeſus; and he alſo ſpeaks of ſome
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:192303:13"/>
that were in Chriſt before him. Now the Quakers, if they are not ſtark blind, may ſee in what ſenſe Chriſt is ſaid to dwell in the Saints; that is, by the Gifts and Graces of his holy Spirit, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 22. the Saints are <hi>the Habitation of God through the Spirit. For if any Man have not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is none of his.</hi> Theſe Gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, Chriſt promiſed, <hi>John 16. 7. I go to my Father, and he will ſend the Comforter,</hi> this Spirit of Truth, to guide into all Truth; which was accordingly poured upon the Apoſtles and Diſciples, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. at large. And <hi>Acts 19. 2. Paul</hi> asks thoſe Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> whether they had <hi>received the Holy Ghoſt ſince they believed?</hi> that is, this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter that Chriſt had promiſed, that when he went to the Father he would ſend, <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 32. and give to them that obey him; albeit the perſonal Aſcenſion of Chriſt is fully witneſſed to. And to put this out of doubt, read <hi>Luke 24. 49, 50, 51. And behold, I ſend the Promiſe of my Father upon you: but tarry ye in the City of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>till ye be endowed with Power from on high;</hi> and then go and proſecute the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I have committed to you: <hi>And he led them out as far as</hi> Bethany, <hi>and he lift up his Hands, and bleſſed them. And it came to paſs, that while he bleſſed them, he was parted from them, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried up into Heaven.</hi> Compare <hi>Act. 1. 9. He was taken up, and a Cloud received him out of their ſight; And while they looked ſtedfaſtly towards Heaven, as he</hi> (that is, Jeſus) <hi>went up, behold, two Men ſtood by them in white Apparel,</hi> which were two An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:192303:14"/>
               <hi>ver. 10. which alſo ſaid, Ye Men of</hi> Galilee, <hi>why ſtand ye gazing up into Heaven? This ſame Jeſus which is taken up from you into Heaven, ſhall ſo come, in like manner as you have ſeen him go into Heaven.</hi> 
               <q>Ay, ſaith <hi>George Whitehead,</hi> in like manner, but every Like is not the ſame: Pitiful ſhift!</q> Thus you plainly ſee the Certainty of Chriſt's Aſcenſion, and that the Holy Ghoſt's Deſcenſion, <hi>Acts 2. 3, 4. &amp; ver.</hi> 38. promiſed to the penitent believing obedient Soul. But <hi>Act. 3. 20, 21. He ſhall ſend Jeſus Chriſt, which before was preached unto you: Whom the Heavens muſt receive, till the times of Reſtitution of all things, which God hath ſpoken by the Mouth of all his holy Prophets ſince the World began.</hi> Now this Reſtitution is not yet, tho the Spirit was come. See <hi>Acts 7. 55. But he</hi> (that is, <hi>Stephen) being full of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> (mark that) <hi>looked ſtedfaſtly up into Heaven, and ſaw the Glory of God, and Jeſus ſtanding on the Right-hand of God:</hi> ver. 56. and there he ſaith, <hi>I ſee the Son of Man ſtanding at the Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand of God.</hi> Obſerve, <hi>Stephen</hi> was full of the Holy Ghoſt, or of the Spirit of Chriſt, when he had this glorious ſight of Chriſt in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens at the Right-hand of God, and in the Glory of the Father. Now it is the Faith of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that Chriſt ſhall come in this glorious Body the ſecond time from Heaven, <hi>Phil. 3. 20, 21. We,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, look for the Saviour, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> not for a greater Fulneſs of the Spirit, as the Quakers dream; for what greater Fulneſs could <hi>Paul</hi> expect, if the <hi>Quakers</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were true, if Heaven and the whole Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:192303:14"/>
were in him before? But, ſaith <hi>Paul, we look for the Saviour, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; who ſhall change our vile Bodies, and make them like his glorious Body.</hi> Yea, ſaith Chriſt, <hi>you ſhall ſee the Son of Man come in Power and great Glory, and every Eye ſhall ſee him,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. 26. It is more than probable, that Chriſt pointed at this Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Impoſtors, the <hi>Quakers,</hi> who ſay, <hi>Behold, he is in the ſecret Chambers, ay, within thee, not at a diſtance from thee. Believe them not,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>for my ſecond coming ſhall be viſible as the Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or the Sun that riſeth in the Eaſt, and ſhines to the Weſt; every Eye ſhall ſee me,</hi> &amp;c. Let this ſerve to conſtrue what they intend in their Paper, when they ſpeak of three Divine Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes bearing Record in Heaven; it is the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven within</hi> they intend.</p>
            <p>III. I proceed to the third Head collected out of their Pamphlet, as propoſed to be examined; and that is, they profeſs to own the Divinity and Humanity of Chriſt. I ſhall therefore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to examine their Belief herein; and ſtill I know no better way, than to make uſe of their own Conſtruing Books, as the ſureſt way not to wrong them: for by comparing this profeſſed Faith with the Writings of ſome of their chief Guides, by that you will ſee whether they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve as they ſay, or whether it be not only a gloſs to deceive the Hearts of the Simple.</p>
            <p>And in examining this Point of Faith profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by them, I ſhall begin with their greatly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired <hi>George Fox,</hi> in his <hi>Great Mystery,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:192303:15"/>
               <hi>p.</hi> 71. he ſays, <hi>Chriſt's Nature is not Humane, which is Earthly, for that is the firſt</hi> Adam. But this looks too bare-fac'd, not the Concluſion drawn from ſome prepared Premiſes. See im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately before; <q>Where doth the Scripture ſpeak of Humane? now we do not deny that Chriſt, according to the Fleſh, was of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> but deny the word Human to be Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-Phraſe.</q> He would by this ſhift perſwade the World, that he doth not deny that Chriſt's Body is conſtituted of Human Nature, being of <hi>Abraham;</hi> but he will not allow the word Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane. Why then do they, in their Pamphlet, ſpeak of the Humanity of Chriſt? But one may diſcern, without Spectacles, that his End is to deny Chriſt's Body of Fleſh. But one would have thought that great <hi>George,</hi> who pretends to tranſlate the Greek into Engliſh, in his Book called, <hi>The Mystery of the Great Whore,</hi> ſhould now have found as much as Humane in the Greek, though not in the Engliſh, it being ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times uſed in the Epiſtles, which in the Latin is <hi>more Hominum Humanorum,</hi> after the manner of Humane; and <q>Chriſt's Human Nature is no more than his Man's Nature, <hi>Smiths</hi>'s <hi>Primmer,</hi> p. 9. <hi>Sword of the Lord,</hi> p. 24.</q> 
               <q>They that are falſe Miniſters, preach Chriſt without; your Carnal Chriſt is utterly denied by the Light.</q> What can be meant here, but the fleſhly Body of Chriſt, or his Humanity? this is <hi>denied by the Light;</hi> that in their ſenſe is the ſame to ſay, That the Divinity denies the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity of Chriſt; moſt horrid Confuſion! But
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:192303:15"/>
would you have it in plainer Terms from their own Pens, then ſee <hi>Pennington</hi>'s <hi>Queſtions,</hi> an eminent <hi>Quaker,</hi> p. 33. who ſpeaks with an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Spirit; <q>This we certainly know, and can never call the bodily Garment, Chriſt, but that which appeared and dwelt in the Body, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> They own that there was ſuch a Man as Jeſus, who was the Son of <hi>Mary,</hi> and that God was in him: But this is no more than what they ſay of themſelves; but the Man Chriſt he calls here, <hi>the bodily Garment,</hi> and ſaith, <hi>they can never call that Chriſt:</hi> So that if this be not fully to deny the Humanity of Chriſt, I know not what is. But ſee what is aſſerted in Mr. <hi>Hicks</hi>'s <hi>Dialogue,</hi> pag. 44, 45. When Mr. <hi>Hicks</hi> hath profeſſed his Faith in the Humanity of Chriſt, namely, <q>That he was the Word made Fleſh, and God manifeſt in the Fleſh, called al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>Immanuel,</hi> or God with us, not the meer Godhead of the Son, nor the meer Manhood, but God and Man united in one Perſon, that is the Chriſt. To which one <hi>Stephen Criſp,</hi> a lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Quaker,</hi> anſwered, Then I know the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Date of thy Chriſt.</q> Mr. <hi>Hicks</hi> asked him, <q>Whether he conſidered what he ſaid?</q> He anſwered, <q>I ſay again, I know the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Date of thy Chriſt.</q> I query whether the plain meaning be not, I know the Beginning and Date, <hi>i. e.</hi> The End of thy Chriſt? And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this be not a total denying of the Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as well as the Humanity of Chriſt? Now what is this, but another Chriſt and Goſpel than that which <hi>Paul</hi> preach'd <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 8, 9.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:192303:16"/>
which he pronounceth <hi>accurſed?</hi> Another Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, <hi>pag.</hi> 45. of <hi>Dialogue,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Richard Stubs,</hi> a <hi>Quaker,</hi> asking <hi>Elizabeth Weatherby, How ſhe expected to be ſaved?</hi> She anſwered, <hi>By that Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus who was born of the Virgin, and died at</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem. <hi>Stubs</hi> told her, <hi>That was the falſe Chriſt, and an Antichriſt.</hi> Horrid Blaſphemy againſt the Son of God! But ſee what <hi>George Fox</hi> ſaith in his <hi>Myſtery,</hi> pag. 206. <q>If there be any other Chriſt but he that was crucified within, he is a falſe Chriſt, or the falſe Chriſt; and he that hath not this Chriſt that was crucified within, is a Reprobate. And <hi>pag.</hi> 207. he ſays, God's Chriſt is not diſtinct from the Saints.</q> I think, here is a bare-faced piece of Blaſphemy, and down-right denying the Lord Chriſt. What, was that the falſe Chriſt that died at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> without the Gates of <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi> 
               <q>Ay, ſaith <hi>George Fox,</hi> if there be any other Chriſt than he that was crucified within, he is the falſe Chriſt.</q> By being <hi>crucified within,</hi> is meant within that Man the Son of <hi>Mary;</hi> not the Man that was crucified was Chriſt, he was but the outward Garment; that is, he that was born of the Virgin, that lived in the World, in Faſtings, Weakneſs and Temptations, Hunger, Thirſt and Wearineſs; that was in an Agony, and ſweat great Drops or Clods of Blood; that was crowned with Thorns, and crucified upon the Croſs without the Gates of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> that was in all Points tempted like as we are, yet without Sin. This they will not allow to be the true Chriſt, or God's Chriſt. Is not this
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:192303:16"/>
plain denying of the Lord that bought them? Surely their groſs Blindneſs, and thick Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, is to be lamented, and that eſpecially ſince they labour to keep a Chriſtian Mask over their Antichriſtian Face. One <hi>Wolrich</hi> a <hi>Quaker,</hi> in his <hi>Declaration to the Baptiſts,</hi> pag. 13. ſays, <q>That Chriſt was never ſeen with any carnal Eyes, nor his Voice heard with any carnal Ears.</q> No, were not the Eyes of the Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude faſtned upon him? Did not the Jews that crucified him, ſee him? Yes, they cannot be ignorant hereof. But the meaning is, that was not the Chriſt that the Jews ſaw and crucified, that was but the outward Garment, the true Chriſt was crucified within that Vail. Thus the Humanity of Chriſt is fully denied, that Man was no more Chriſt, on their account, than <hi>George Fox.</hi> And, <hi>Saul</hi>'s <hi>Errand to Damaſcus,</hi> pag. 9. they ſay, That <hi>Chriſt hath no Body but his Church.</hi> But I ſhall refer you to Mr. <hi>Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tham</hi>'s Book, <hi>Chriſtianiſmus Primitivus,</hi> Book 4. Treatiſe 11. where you have an Account of a Conference betwixt <hi>Thomas Granthan</hi> and <hi>John Whitehead<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> a <hi>Quaker,</hi> about Chriſt having a Body of Fleſh and Bones; which <hi>John Whitehead</hi> denied him to have, and deridingly asked <hi>Tho. Grantham, What a one that Body was, and how big?</hi> To which Mr. <hi>Grantham</hi> replied, <hi>Such a one as mine, or any other Man's, Sin and Corruption only excepted.</hi> Now <hi>John Whitehead</hi> falls to uſing that Craft, without which Quakeriſm would ſoon be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed. <hi>Well,</hi> Thomas, ſaith he, <hi>I will ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy thee, if I can: I ſay, Chriſt's Fleſh was
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:192303:17"/>
ſuch as</hi> Tho. Grantham'<hi>s Fleſh, all Corruption ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted.</hi> One would have thought <hi>J. W.</hi> had fairly owned the Humanity of Chriſt here: But <hi>Tho. Grantham</hi> being ſuſpicious, asks him one honeſt Queſtion more, <hi>Doſt thou not mean, by all Corruption excepted, my whole Body, and the Fleſh of all Men?</hi> But now, inſtead of anſwering this Queſtion. <hi>J. W.</hi> curſed <hi>T. G.</hi> in theſe words, <hi>Thou whited Wall, God ſhall ſmite thee; the Plagues, and Curſes, and Vengeance of God is thy Portion.</hi> To which <hi>Thomas Grantham</hi> replied, <hi>I am taught of God, not to render Railing for Railing,</hi> &amp;c. So that <hi>J. W.</hi> if he could, would have had his counterfeit Coin have paſſed muſter, in his meaning, which appeared to be this, Chriſt had a Body like another Man, all the Body and Fleſh of another Man excepted; then Chriſt muſt have no Human Body at all; ſo that this was politick Prieſt-craft indeed.</p>
            <p>From all that hath been ſaid, what can be more clear, than that theſe People really deny the Humanity of Chriſt, the Lord that bought them? I ſhall conclude this Head, with an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance or two more: Several Queries being put to <hi>Edward Burroughs,</hi> (a Man famous amongſt the <hi>Quakers</hi>) whoſe Works are a large Folio; the famous Epithets, and honourable commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datory Epiſtles that are prefix'd before his Works, by <hi>Whitehead, Fox,</hi> and others, would even daunt a modeſt Pen to tranſcribe. The Queries are ſaid to be propounded to <hi>Burroughs,</hi> by one <hi>Philip Bennet;</hi> they are no leſs than twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which you have repeated, with their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:192303:17"/>
in the Book aforeſaid, from <hi>pag.</hi> 29, to 34. at large, which will be too tedious to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe: I ſhall give you two or three, with their Anſwers, and by that you may gueſs at the reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> 3. <q>Whether did the Man Chriſt real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and indeed ſuffer in his own Perſon, for that End, and after the ſame manner as he did up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Croſs at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> before that time, or ſince that time?</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quaker</hi>'s Anſwer; <q>Here, thou full of all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty, haſt manifeſted thy Poiſon and Enmity; but thou art ſeen with the Light, and with it condemned for ever: Chriſt Jeſus, in his own Perſon, doth, and ever did, ſuffer by thee, and ſuch as thou art: After the ſame manner, thou blind Phariſee and Blaſphemer, wouldſt thou have Chriſt have more Ends in Suffering than one.</q> 
               <hi>Burroughs, Ibid.</hi> p. 30.</p>
            <p>You ſee here what a railing Anſwer this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Father gives: Let the Reader judg whether the Anſwer hath not more like Poiſon and Blaſphemy in it, than the Queſtion. But the Deſign of the Queſtion is not to be born, and a direct Anſwer muſt not be given, for they believe not the Sufferings in that <hi>outward Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> as they call it, upon the Croſs, to be the one Offering, or alone Sacrifice, nor any more availa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as is eaſily made appear, than the Sufferings in his Saints; yet, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 10, 14. the Body of Jeſus is ſaid to be <hi>offered once for all;</hi> and it is called <hi>the Offering of one Sacrifice.</hi> But this they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure to hear of, but conclude Chriſt to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:192303:18"/>
be crucified in them, as well as in that Man at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> as appears in his Anſwer to the <hi>2d</hi> Query, that being too large to tranſcribe, take the Concluſion of it thus; <q>Thou Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, which lookeſt at Chriſt's Death at <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> alone; ſo let all they that are thy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, ſee what they hold up that follow thee.</q> 
               <hi>Edw. Burroughs,</hi> p. 30.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> 4. <q>Was not that Death which the Man Chriſt ſuffered once, and but once upon the Croſs at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſo ſatisfactory for all the Sins of the Elect, as that the Juſtice of God did not, doth not require any ſuffering or working upon that account, either from Sinners or Saints?</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quaker</hi> 
               <q>Here thou Jeſuit art pleading for a Chriſt afar off thee; that Chriſt that died at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> did not ſatisfy for thee, who art an Enemy to him, and art under the Woe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> And after ſpending many Lines in uttering the like invective Stuff, he concludes, <q>Let all Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſee whether thou be not a blind ignorant Sot.</q> 
               <hi>Ibid.</hi> p. 30, 31.</p>
            <p>It ſeems it is Jeſuitical to plead for him to be the Chriſt that died at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> on the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi>'s account; it is not to be ſuffered by <hi>Edw. Burroughs,</hi> for the Queriſt to plead for a Chriſt afar off. It is too large to repeat the blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous ſelf-contradictions Railings included in this Anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> 5. <q>Whether you be reconciled to God by any other Obedience, than that very Obedience which Chriſt performed in his own
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:192303:18"/>
Perſon? or by any Sufferings or Death, than that which Chriſt ſuffered upon the Croſs at <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quaker.</hi> 
               <q>Silence Fleſh; wouldſt thou, who art an Enemy to God, know how we are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to God, and by what Obedience? Own the Light in thy Conſcience, and be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to that, then thou ſhalt know by what Obedience we are reconciled to God; for yet thou knoweſt no Obedience, but art an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to the Croſs of Chriſt, and in the Myſtery of Iniquity, and in the dark Power of the Man of Sin: What haſt thou to do to talk of Obedience? thou art blind, and in the broad way that leads to Death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>p.</hi> 32.</q>
            </p>
            <p>It is not worth while to give you a Repetition of his Bedlam-like Anſwers to theſe twenty ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Queſtions; take a Breviat of his profound, ſober and convincing Anſwers (you have them at large in <hi>Burroughs</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s Works, from <hi>pag.</hi> 29, to 34.) as followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Thou Reprobate, and Child of Darkneſs, the Light condemns thee and thy Generation eternally: We witneſs thee to be in the Sorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Witchcraft: thou art Darkneſs it ſelf, thou Dragon; thy Queries are conjured in the Black Art, out of the Bottomleſs Pit, thou Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viner; we witneſs thee to be the Beaſt which wars with the Lamb; thou Antichriſt, which lookeſt at Chriſt's Death at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> alone; thou art ſeen with the Light, and with it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, thou blind Phariſee and Blaſphemer: Thou Jeſuit, art thou pleading for a Chriſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:192303:19"/>
afar off thee? Thou art under the Wo, and from that Wo thou ſhalt never hee. Let all People ſee whether thou be not a blind igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Sot; here thou replieſt thy ſottiſh Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries concerning the Body of Jeſus, as the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil did about the Body of <hi>Moſes;</hi> thou diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient One, upon whom God will render Vengeance in flaming Fire; thou art accurſed, thou Beaſt, to whom the Plagues of God are due, upon whom the Wrath of God muſt be accompliſhed; thou art ſhut out from God for ever, thou blind Hypocrite;</q> and much more to the ſame purpoſe. But let this ſuffice to ſhew you the immediate Inſpirations of theſe perfect Men: And after he hath uttered theſe railing, curſing and condemning Anſwers, he concludes thus; <q>Bleſſed be the Lord that hath diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered thee! ſo thy Queries are anſwered in the Eternal Life and Light of God, and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is given upon thee and them, which thou ſhalt eternally witneſs. Thy Queries are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered lovingly, and plainly, and in the Scripture-Language and Terms; and with the Eternal Light and Life of God, ſet thee in thy own Place, which thou ſhalt eternally witneſs.</q> 
               <hi>Ibid.</hi> p. 34.</p>
            <p>This famous Piece had its birth into the World in the Year 1672. But was there ever ſuch a Bundle of Blaſphemy, Curſings and Damnings, (uttered upon no Provocation) from the vileſt Heathen, or from <hi>Muggleton</hi> himſelf? and that which is worſt of all, he entitles this to the <hi>Eternal Life and Light of God.</hi> Could
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:192303:19"/>
the Devil himſelf have been more vile and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digiouſly arrogant, to take upon him to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine a Man's endleſs Condition? Let all that are, or would be Chriſtians, ſay with <hi>Jacob,</hi> Gen. 49. 6. <hi>O my Soul, come not thou into their Secrets; unto their Aſſembly, my Honour, be not thou united.</hi> Let this ſerve for confutation of their pretending to own the Humanity of Chriſt; and let all Chriſtians believe in that Jeſus that was crucified without the Gates of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that died, was buried, and roſe again. <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 39. ſaith Chriſt, <hi>It is I my ſelf; Behold my Hands and my Feet; handle and ſee, for a Spirit hath not Fleſh and Bones, as you ſee me have.</hi> This I ſay is the Chriſt of God, as <hi>Peter</hi> teſtifies, <hi>Acts 2. 36. Therefore let all the Houſe of</hi> Iſrael <hi>know aſſuredly, that God hath made the ſame Jeſus whom ye crucified, both Lord and Chriſt.</hi> I paſs this, and leave what hath been ſaid, and the Opinion of the <hi>Quakers</hi> about the Humanity of Chriſt, to impartial Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration.</p>
            <p>But leſt any ſhould ſuppoſe the <hi>Quakers</hi> do not own ſuch blaſphemous, condemning and railing Anſwers, as <hi>Edw. Burroughs</hi> gave to the twenty Queſtions before hinted at, ſome of which being about the Perſon or Humanity of Chriſt, and Place of his Reſidence; you have Mr. <hi>Penn</hi> warranting this Anſwer from God, and by the ſenſe of the Eternal Spirit; for he declares, <q>It was the Portion, and only fit An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to be given to thoſe trapanning Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: and, ſaith he, had <hi>Edw. Burroughs</hi> gone
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:192303:20"/>
into a familiar opening unto his vulterous un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean ſerpertine Eye, all the deep Things of the Spirit of God, and Myſteries of Holy Kingdom, who was in that nature that cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the Lord of them, <hi>Edw. Burroughs</hi> had brought the Wrath of the Eternal God upon himſelf, inſtead of the Prieſt.</q> 
               <hi>Will. Penn</hi>'s <hi>Reaſ. againſt Railing,</hi> p. 164.</p>
            <p>IV. They profeſs in their Pamphlet, That they believe and expect Salvation and Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the Righteouſneſs and Merits of Chriſt, and not by their own Righteouſneſs or Works; and that they believe Remiſſion of Sins, and Redemption through the Death, Sufferings and Bloodſhed of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>This they make a plenary profeſſion of, in their Anſwer to their third and fourth Queſtions propounded. I muſt now examine whether they believe what they have here ſo plauſibly profeſſed: And there are three things to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired into, which together with the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances and Concomitants, will unfold their meaning in what they have here profeſſed.</p>
            <p>1. What do the Quakers intend by the Death and Blood of Chriſt? They do not believe in that Blood that was ſhed upon the Croſs; for <hi>Robert Ruckhill,</hi> a Quaker, ſaith, in his Paper ſent to <hi>Tho. Grantham,</hi> 
               <q>That the Blood of Chriſt, or Blood of Sprinkling, never mortal Eye beheld. And in <hi>pag.</hi> 11. of the ſame Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, he condemns all Profeſſors that know no other Blood of Sprinkling than that which
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:192303:20"/>
the Jews ſaw.</q> So that the Blood that our dear Lord ſhed upon the Croſs, they do not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend; for, <hi>John</hi> 19. 34. the Souldier pierced his Side, and Water and Blood came out of his Wounds, in the piercing of his Hands and Feet; this the Souldiers and his Crucifiers ſaw. But this is not the Blood intended; ſee <hi>Tho. Lawſon</hi>'s Book, <hi>pag.</hi> 18. I ſuppoſe they will not deny him to be a thorow-paced Quaker; he ſaith, <q>The offering of Chriſt's Body to be broken, and his Blood to be ſhed, avails not, ſo as through Faith therein to ſet free from Sin; but Blood in a Myſtery, and a Body in a Myſtery, which we know not what it is, ſaith <hi>Lawſon.</hi> But (ſaith <hi>Pennington</hi>'s <hi>Queſtions,</hi> pag. 33.) this we certainly know, and can never call the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily Garment, Chriſt;</q> That is, in plain Engliſh, that Body of Fleſh that they can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver call Chriſt. <hi>Pennington</hi> in another Page of the ſame Book, asks, <q>Can outward Blood cleanſe the Conſcience? we witneſs the ſame Chriſt that ever was, now manifeſt in the Fleſh.</q> This <hi>Iſaac Pennington</hi> was an appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Quaker.</p>
            <p>Now if this be not the Myſtery of Iniquity, I know not what may be called ſo; and it this be not to bring in thoſe damnable Hereſies, <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the Lord that bought them,</hi> 2 Pet. 2. 1. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied of by <hi>Peter,</hi> what is? for the Blood ſhed upon the Croſs, is not available, ſay they. Now why ſhould theſe Impoſtors talk of the Blood of Chriſt, and labour to perſwade the World that they expect Juſtification, Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:192303:21"/>
and Salvation, and the bleſſed Effects of his Suffering and Dying, even Salvation? See <hi>Pennington's Queſtions,</hi> pag. 25. <q>Can outward Blood cleanſe the Conſcience? can outward Water waſh the Soul clean?</q> What plainer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial can there be of the Efficacy of the Blood of Chriſt ſhed on the Croſs? <hi>E. Burrough</hi>'s <hi>Trumpet,</hi> &amp;c. p. 17. <q>All the Presbyterians and Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, with their feeding upon the Report of a thing done many hundred Years ago.</q> Thus they deridingly ſpeak of ſuch as believe in the Death and Sufferings of Chriſt upon the Croſs. I ſhall conclude this Confutation of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Profeſſion of Faith in the Blood of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now if the Quakers will aſſign ſome other Blood of Chriſt, beſides the Blood of the Man Chriſt Jeſus crucified on the Croſs, that is of this redeeming Nature and Efficacy, then I ſhall be inclined to turn Quaker, and not before. But let Chriſtians believe in Chriſt's Death and Blood-ſhed upon the Croſs, for Juſtification, Sanctification and Redemption, and let the Word of God be true, and theſe Men Liars, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 25. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 5. It was this Chriſt Jeſus that was crucified upon the Croſs, that loved us, <hi>and waſhed us from our Sins in his own Blood.</hi> Heb. 9. 14. Col. 1. 14. <hi>We have Redemption through his Blood.</hi> Heb. 13. 12. <hi>Wherefore Jeſus alſo, that he may ſanctify the People with his own Blood, ſuffered without the Gate,</hi> &amp;c. See <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 9, 10. <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 20. Let us believe that Chriſt's Blood ſhed upon the Croſs, was to reconcile us
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:192303:21"/>
to God: Let us for ever admire God for this unſpeakable Gift of his Son to die for us, <hi>that he by the Grace of God ſhould taſte Death for every Man,</hi> Heb. 2. 9.</p>
            <p>Again; Let us believe, love and obey ſo dear a Lord, that ſo freely gave his Body to be broken, pierced and mangled in that ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful manner, to redeem, ſanctify and juſtify ſuch that lay hold upon him: <hi>Let the Love of Chriſt conſtrain us to be followers of God as dear Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and walk in Love as Chriſt hath loved us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. Under this fourth Head they pretend to believe and expect Juſtification and Remiſſion of Sins by the Righteouſneſs and Merits of Chriſt, and Redemption by him.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now examine, whether they do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and expect Juſtification, and Remiſſion of Sins by the Righteouſneſs and Merits of Chriſt?</p>
            <p>Now if you will believe their Writings, you will ſee this their Profeſſion to be but a painted and deceitful Flouriſh: for Juſtification and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Sins by the Righteouſneſs of another, is not by them believed.</p>
            <p>See <hi>Edw Burrough</hi>'s Works in Anſwer to the <hi>14<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> Query, <hi>p.</hi> 33. <q>God doth not accept any where there is any failing, or who do not fulfil the Law, and anſwer every Demand of Juſtice. This, were there no other Inſtance, confutes their plauſible pretence to Juſtification and Remiſſion by the Righteouſneſs and Merits of Chriſt.</q> But ſee <hi>Will. Pen's Sandy Foundat.</hi> p. 25, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               <q>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication is not from the Imputation of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:192303:22"/>
Righteouſneſs, but from the actual per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming and keeping God's righteous Statutes.</q> How is there Remiſſion and Juſtification by the Merits of Chriſt, according to their Profeſſion in their Pamphlet, when it muſt be by the perfect and exact Performance of the Law of God in the Creature? <hi>Lawſon</hi>'s Book, <hi>p.</hi> 18. affirms, <q>That the offering of Chriſt's Body to be broken, and his Blood to be ſhed, avails not, ſo as through Faith therein to ſet free from Sin.</q> What is this but a plain denying Remiſſion of Sins by the Blood of Chriſt? And ſeeing we have Inſtances enow, or too many, why ſhould we ſpare them? <hi>Will. Pen</hi> ſpeaks out: See <hi>Apolog.</hi> p. 148. <q>Juſtification by the Righteouſneſs of another, or which Chriſt fulfilled for us in his own Perſon wholly without us, we boldly affirm to be a Doctrine of Devils, and an Arm of the Sea of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, which doth now deluge the World.</q> See alſo Mr. <hi>Pen's Sandy Foundation,</hi> p. 25,—30. <q>It is a great Abomination to ſay, God ſhould condemn and puniſh his Innocent Son, that he having ſatisfied for our Sins, we may be juſtified by the Imputation of his perfect Righteouſneſs.</q> O why ſhould this horrible thing be contended for by Chriſtians! O, and why ſhould the Quakers be ſuch grand Delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, as ſo plainly pretend to believe it, and ſay he died for your Sins, and roſe again for your Juſtification! when, <hi>ibid.</hi> p. 16. Mr. <hi>Pen</hi> ſaith, <q>That the Conſequences of ſuch a Doctrine is both irreligious and irrational.</q>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:192303:22"/>
And why ſhould they believe Juſtification by Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, ſince <hi>Tho. Lucock</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fimed, <q>That he was as perfect without Sin as God is; and blames others becauſe they ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>In many things we offend all?</hi> and this Doctrine of Perfection, that is, a Sinleſs living, is the known Doctrine of the Quakers.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But let not Chriſtians ſay they are without Sin, leſt they deceive themſelves, as the Quakers do, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1. 8. And let us believe that the Lord laid upon Chriſt our Redeemer the Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities of us all, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. 6. <hi>And as by one Man's Diſobedience many were made Sinners; ſo by the Obedience of one, ſhall many be made righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> Rom. 5. 18.</p>
            <p>3. They profeſs to believe Redemption and Salvation by Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Let us examine what they intend by Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: <hi>Firſt,</hi> Not Redemption of their Bodies from the Graves of the Earth, for this is poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively denied by them; tho all Chriſtians own it as a great Article of the Chriſtian Faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Then what is to be redeemed and ſaved, not the Soul; for <hi>George Fox</hi> ſaith that is part of God, without Beginning or End; ſurely then it needs no Redemption: and God did not ſend his Son to redeem himſelf. Take the natural ſenſe of what is expreſt, <hi>Great My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery,</hi> p. 29, and p. 90. See further what <hi>George Keith</hi> ſaith, <q>Chriſt came to ſave that which was loſt, and that which was loſt is ſtill in Man's Heart, and there it muſt be ſought, for
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:192303:23"/>
it remains ſtill in the Houſe; that is, Man's Heart; this is the thing to be ſought for; this Chriſt came to ſeek and to ſave: and all his Miniſters preached People to this, the Loſt in Man, that it may be found; a loſt God, a loſt Chriſt, this was the ſum and ſubſtance of their Doctrine.</q> 
               <hi>G. Keith, Immediat. Inſpirat.</hi> p 75, 76. May we not think <hi>G. K.</hi> to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired by the Prince of Darkneſs? or that he had loſt the very Light of Nature, to talk of a loſt God, and a loſt Chriſt to be ſought and ſaved? O were ever God and Chriſt in a loſt Condition! But poor Man was, and we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve he came to ſeek and ſave Sinners, who had loſt the Image and Favour of God. You may ſee more to this purpoſe, <hi>Fox's Great Myſtery,</hi> p. 100. at large.</p>
            <p>Neither do they believe any other Salvation than what they are in the Enjoyment of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready: ſee <hi>Lawſon</hi>'s Book, <hi>p.</hi> 9,—19. ſee two Paſſages in <hi>Nailor</hi>'s Book, <hi>Love to the Loſt,</hi> p. 47, 48, 30. <q>There is a Seed to which the Promiſe of Redemption is, which Seed is that which only wants Redemption, <hi>p.</hi> 30. he ſaith, Chriſt is the Election and Elect Seed.</q> 
               <hi>Fox's Great Myſtery,</hi> p. 224. tells us, The Seed to which <q>the Promiſe is, is that which hath been laden as a Cart with Sheaves by Sinners, which Seed is the hope Chriſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The natural Conſequence of this Doctrine is, that Chriſt came to redeem Chriſt, a loſt God, and a loſt Chriſt, as before ſaid. Might not the Heavens bluſh, and the Earth tremble at ſuch
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:192303:23"/>
blaſphemous Abſurdities! But I ſhall not in this ſhort Diſcourſe trace them in their groſs Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions of Truth, and each other, about the Light within, the Seed, Chriſt, and the Word. But let this ſuffice to confute and unmask their pretended Belief aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>V. They profeſs to own and believe the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Offices of Chriſt in his Church, that he is both King, Prieſt and Prophet to, and over his Church and People.</p>
            <p>I ſhall proceed to examine the Truth of this Profeſſion, which if it were true, were very comprehenſive of a great part of the Chriſtian Religion. But what hath been made appear already, ſhews us, that by no means their word muſt be taken.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt;</hi> How do they believe the Kingly Office of Chriſt, are they not miſtaken? Let us exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine ſome Appellations that they have taken from Chriſt and given to <hi>Geo. Fox</hi> ſenior. See a Book entituled, <hi>Tyranny and Hypocriſy detected,</hi> p. 18, 19. <hi>Sol. Eckles</hi> celebrates <hi>Geo. Fox</hi> thus, <q>Bleſſed be the Man that came out of the North; bleſſed be the Womb that bear him, and the Breaſts that gave him Suck: and <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>p.</hi> 19. a Letter written by <hi>Joſias Coal,</hi> a Quaker, from <hi>Barbadoes</hi> to <hi>G. Fox,</hi> 21 day, <hi>12th</hi> Month, 1658. <q>Dear <hi>George Fox,</hi> who art the Father of many Nations, whoſe Life hath reached through us thy Children, even to the Iſles afar off, to the begetting of many again to a live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hope; for which Generations to come ſhall
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:192303:24"/>
call thee Bleſſed; whoſe Being and Habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is in the Power of the Higheſt, in which thou ruleſt and governeſt in Righteouſneſs, and thy Kingdom is eſtabliſhed in Peace, and the Increaſe thereof is without end.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now what is more apparent than that by theſe Appellations, the Scepter is wreſted out of Chriſt's Hands, and given to <hi>G. Fox?</hi> Now this Letter was not judged by the infallible Spirit of the inſpired Elders to be a tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Flaſh of a miſguided Zeal: For <hi>G. Fox</hi> and his Peers ordered it to be recorded amongſt things worthy to be regiſter'd, tho the Contents of it would make a modeſt Heathen bluſh and tremble. Take the Contents particularly.</p>
            <p>1. He doth expreſly aſcribe to him a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; <q>Thy Kingdom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and thou ruleſt and governeſt.</q> Now he that rules and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns in his own Kingdom, muſt of neceſſity be an actual King.</p>
            <p>2. He deſcribes to us the Subjects of this Kingdom, who, next to himſelf, are <hi>Joſiah Coal,</hi> and the Elders or Peers, whom he calls, <q>us thy Children; and remotely, thoſe to whom the Life of <hi>G. Fox</hi> hath reached through the Elders, to the begetting them again to a lively hope, and they are many, therefore he calls him the Father of many Nations.</q>
            </p>
            <p>3. He tells us what kind of Power and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority it is in which this King rules and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns, and that is, in the Power of the Higheſt, a Spiritual and Divine Power, not like that of the Kingdoms of Men.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:192303:24"/>4. We have here the Stability of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; 'Thy Kingdom is eſtabliſhed in Peace.</p>
            <p>5. The Extent of this Kingdom; <q>The En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe thereof is without End, it is a bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Kingdom.</q>
            </p>
            <p>6. The Excellency of this King is ſuch, and his Happineſs ſo great, that, <q>Not only the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Age, but Generations to come ſhall call him <hi>Bleſſed.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>So that here you ſee <hi>G. F.</hi> fully inveſted and throned in Chriſt's Kingly Office; and why ſhould the Quakers be angry, as they have been, for calling <hi>G. Fox</hi> the <hi>King of the Quakers,</hi> ſince he is as really ſo on their account, as Chriſt is the <hi>King of Chriſtians.</hi> I ſuppoſe all Chriſtians conclude, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9. 6, 7. where ſeveral of theſe Terms are included, to be ſpoken of Chriſt, as <hi>the Prince of Peace; Of the increaſe of his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Peace, there ſhall be no End,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 32, 33. and <hi>he ſhall reign over the Houſe of</hi> Jacob <hi>for ever, and of his Kingdom there ſhall be no End. Luke 11. 27. Bleſſed be the Womb that bare thee</hi> (G. Fox) <hi>and the Breaſts that gave thee ſuck.</hi> And <hi>Iſa. 9. 6. Everlaſting Father,</hi> or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Ages to come. Heb. 2. 13. <hi>Behold, I, and the Children which God haſt given me. Mich.</hi> 5. 4. And he ſhall ſtand, and feed, or rule in the ſtrength of the Lord, <hi>&amp;c. He ſhall be great to the ends of the Earth.</hi> Now one would have thought, that ſuch Expreſſions as theſe, out of which <hi>Coal</hi> and <hi>Eckels</hi> had theirs, might have intended Chriſt: But you ſee theſe divine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-inſpired Men, by virtue of their immediate
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:192303:25"/>
Revelations, apply them to <hi>George Fox,</hi> with blaſphemous Confidence enough.</p>
            <p>But it may be they will ſay, That the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures mentioned, point at Chriſt as the Figure or Type, and <hi>G. Fox</hi> as the Subſtance; for they ſay, in <hi>Saul</hi>'s Errand to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> p. 6, 7. <hi>That Chriſt in the Fleſh was a Figure.</hi> And where-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 2 <hi>Cor. 5. 10. We muſt ſtand before the Judgment Seat of Chriſt;</hi> and, <hi>that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath committed all Judgment to the Son.</hi> But read <hi>p. 6, 7. Saul</hi>'s <hi>Errand to Damaſcus,</hi> and <hi>George Fox</hi> takes the Name to himſelf, ſaying, <hi>He is the Eternal Judg of Quick and Dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it may be it is the Chriſt in <hi>George Fox,</hi> that hath this Regal or Kingly Power. But why then was it not ſo expreſſed, <hi>P. 44, 45. Tyranny and Hypocriſy detected,</hi> ſaith <hi>Rebekah Trevers,</hi> a great Propheteſs amongſt them, <q>If ſhe had a Motion from the Lord, as ſhe believed, yet if <hi>George Fox</hi> did not own it to be ſo, ſhe would deny it.</q> So that <hi>George Fox</hi> is not only a King of the Quakers, but alſo of the Light or Chriſt in them, for thoſe believed Motions muſt give way to the Motions of <hi>George Fox. Spirit of the Hat,</hi> pag. 27. you have this ſaying of King <hi>George</hi> repeated, <q>Friends, although I have not told it you, I do now declare it, I have power to bind and looſe whom I pleaſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> Ay, and well he may, ſince he hath deprived Chriſt of his Kingly Office. Now who can imagine that theſe Men can believe the Kingly Office of Chriſt, who thus ſtrip him of his Regal Power? But it may be the Quakers will ſay, It is not
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:192303:25"/>
               <hi>George Fox,</hi> but the Light, or Chriſt within him, that aſſumes this Kingly Power.</p>
            <p>Well, and if the ſame Light and Chriſt be in another, muſt the Chriſt in <hi>George Fox</hi> rule or reign over the ſame Chriſt in another? for, it ſeems, the Light, or Chriſt's Motions in <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bekah Trevers</hi> muſt be denied and rejected, if the Light or Chriſt in <hi>G. Fox</hi> oppoſeth it; ſo that then Chriſt reigns as King over Chriſt. But who <hi>G. Fox</hi> left to ſway this Scepter I know not, except it was <hi>G. Fox</hi> junior, who in his Book, <hi>pag.</hi> 53, 54, 55. you may obſerve him ſpeaking thus; <q>I will make you know, that I the Light, which lighteth every Man that cometh into the World, that all through me ſhould believe, am the true Eternal God which created all things, that by me, the Light, all things are upheld, and that there is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother beſides me can ſave; and I will purge out all your Iniquities, and forgive all your Treſpaſſes; and I will change your Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and I will make you new Creatures, if you will hearken to me, and obey me the Light in you. What I have here written is the words of the Father, who is one with Chriſt the Son, gave me to write, in which words the true Chriſt is renewed, and a Teſtimony given of him, and no other.</q> But this is more than enough of this Blaſphemy againſt the Son of God. So that it appears to every ſeeing Eye, that the Quakers do not own the Kingly Office of Chriſt that died at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> no more, no nor ſo much neither as the Kingly Office of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:192303:26"/>
               <hi>George Fox;</hi> for the Laws of Chriſt are made null by him, and the Ordinances of King Jeſus contemned and rejected by him, as being more powerful and infallible, as may further appear anon.</p>
            <p>2. I ſhall examine how they own Chriſt's Prieſtly Office, which upon diligent ſearch will appear nothing ſo as profeſſed by them, but a meer flouriſh to delude the Ignorant and Eaſy. And that the Quakers deny the Prieſtly, Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory or Advocatory Office of Chriſt, will appear for theſe Reaſons.</p>
            <p>1. They deny the Perſon or Humanity of Chriſt, as hath been before ſhewed; then they cannot own Chriſt's Prieſtly Office, for 1 <hi>Tim. 2. 5. There is one Mediator betwixt God and Man, the Man Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Now if Chriſt hath no Body but his Church, as when occaſion calls for it, I ſhall ſhew: But let what hath been before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid ſuffice at preſent; then I argue thus:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> If Chriſt had a Body that was broken for the Church; then he had a Body beſides the Church: but he had a Body broken for the Church. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Major</hi> is out of doubt, or elſe he gave his Church to be broken for his Church, which is abſurd.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> is proved from <hi>Mat. 26. 26. Luk.</hi> 22. 19. where Chriſt ſaith of his Body, that it was broken for them. Now if the Quakers ſay, Chriſt was never ſeen with any carnal Eye, and that he hath no Body but his Church, it will
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:192303:26"/>
appear they deny the Mediator, the Man Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>2. They deny the Place where Chriſt our High-Prieſt is enter'd, which is the Heavens, the Holy of Holies, according to <hi>Heb. 4. 14. Seeing then that we have a great High-Prieſt, that is paſſed into the Heavens, Jeſus the Son of God, let us hold faſt our Profeſſion.</hi> But ſee what the Quakers ſay, <hi>Smith</hi>'s <hi>Primmer,</hi> p. 8, 9. <q>They that are falſe Miniſters, preach Chriſt without, and bid People believe in him as he is in Heaven above: but they that are true, preach Chriſt within.</q> It ſeems by the Quakers, it is falſe Doctrine to teach People as <hi>Paul</hi> taught the Hebrews, namely, that their Mediator is in Heaven, that their High-Prieſt is there.</p>
            <p>
               <q>They that are falſe Miniſters preach Chriſt without; your Carnal Chriſt is utterly denied by the Light; your<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> imagined God beyond the Stars. But none can witneſs this whoſe Eye is outward, looking at a Redeemer afar off, <hi>&amp;c. Smith</hi>'s <hi>Primmer,</hi> p. 9.</q> 
               <hi>Sword of the Lord,</hi> p. 24. <hi>Shield of Truth,</hi> p. 30. But there hath been enough of this before. They deny any other Heaven than what is within them, as hath manifeſtly appeared.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> Thoſe that deny Chriſt to be entred into the glorious Heavens above, deny the Prieſtly Office of Chriſt: But the Quakers deny Chriſt to be entered into the glorious Heavens above. <hi>Ergo,</hi> they deny the Prieſtly Office of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:192303:27"/>The <hi>Minor</hi> hath been before proved; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the Quakers deny Chriſt to be in the glorious Heavens above.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Major</hi> is evident from Scripture, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 14. <hi>Seeing then that we have a great High-Prieſt, that is paſſed into the Heavens, Jeſus the Son of God.</hi> Heb. 8. 1. <hi>We have ſuch an High-Prieſt, who is ſet on the Right-hand of the Throne of the Majeſty in the Heavens. Burrough</hi>'s Works, <hi>p.</hi> 127. <q>They that deny Chriſt to be the Light in every Man, are Antichriſts.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Smith</hi>'s Primmer, <hi>p.</hi> 8, 9. <q>The falſe Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters preach Chriſt in Heaven, ſaith <hi>Smith</hi> the Quaker, and the true preach Chriſt within, and theſe have no more Fellowſhip together than the Eaſt and Weſt.</q> So that there is juſt ſo much difference betwixt the Doctrine of the Apoſtles and Quakers, as there is between Eaſt and Weſt.</p>
            <p>3. They deny the Blood of the Sacrifice, Chriſt our High-Prieſt offered upon the Croſs. This I have before proved, and ſhewed the ſcornful Contempt they have caſt upon it at large. And much more might be ſaid if need were; what elſe means their dropping ſuch words as theſe? Says <hi>Edw. Billing,</hi> 
               <q>The Myſtery of Iniquity lies in the Blood of Chriſt.</q> And ſay they, <q>Doſt look at Chriſt's Death afar off? What will that Blood avail? didſt ever ſee any of it, that carnal Blood! Can outward Blood cleanſe? if thou hadſt a great deal of it, would it do thee any good?</q> How appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently do they ſcorn that Blood of Chriſt ſhed
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:192303:27"/>
upon the Croſs? But it's moſt evident they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Chriſt's Prieſtly Office.</p>
            <p>4. The Quakers cannot believe the Prieſtly or Mediatory Office of Chriſt, becauſe they have no need of a Mediator. For if they are as perfect without Sin as God is, ſays <hi>Leucock,</hi> and are come to the end of Faith, as ſaith <hi>Lawſon</hi>'s Book, <hi>p.</hi> 10. And if <hi>Burrough</hi>'s Works, <hi>p.</hi> 33. ſay true, <q>That God doth not accept any, where there is any failing, or who doth not fulfil the Law, and anſwer every Demand of Juſtice: and this they ſay they do, and are perfect; then what need have they of the Mediatory Office of Chriſt?</q> It is certain Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians own a Perfection, according to <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 1. to be ſincere; and as our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Be ye perfect.</hi> Secondly, We believe a Perfection through the Merits and Interceſſion of Chriſt, <hi>Philip.</hi> 3. 12. <hi>Not as tho I were already perfect. For if we ſay we have no Sin, we ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive our ſelves,</hi> as the Quakers do. But 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. 1. <hi>If any Man ſin, we have an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate with the Father, Jeſus Chriſt the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous:</hi> In and through him the Saints expected Perfection.</p>
            <p>But Chriſtians alſo expect compleat Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection when they come to Glory, on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide of the Grave; even when Mortality is ſwallowed up of Life.</p>
            <p>But the Quakers believe they have the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt, and are in the glorious Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of it already. But that they are not, I prove thus.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:192303:28"/>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> Thoſe that are in the Poſſeſſion of that Kingdom, neither marry nor are given in Marriage, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But the Quakers do marry, and are given in Marriage: <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Quakers are not in the Poſſeſſion of that Kingdom.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> is ſelf-evident; that they do marry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Major</hi> is proved from our Lord's words. But let what hath been ſaid ſuffice to make it appear, that the Quakers deny the Prieſtly Office of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly,</hi> I ſhall proceed to examine how they own his Prophetick Office, which they ſay, yes verily we believe and own, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now how can it be, ſince they have ſo plainly denied Chriſt's Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Body? as hath been ſhewed. And <hi>Deut.</hi> 18. 15. <hi>The Lord thy God will raiſe up unto thee a Prophet from the midſt of thee, of thy Brethren, like unto me, (i. e.</hi> a Man) <hi>unto him ſhall ye hearken:</hi> he ſhall be <hi>according as you deſired of the Lord in</hi> Horeb, <hi>v.</hi> 16. You were afraid of God's ſpeaking to you; he ſhall raiſe you up a Prophet, a Man, the Man Chriſt Jeſus, of your Brethren, like to me; you ſhall not be terrified with the immediate Voice of God, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 19. Now this is Chriſt, whom <hi>Peter</hi> ſhews and declares, <hi>Acts</hi> 3. 22. <hi>Him ſhall ye hear in all things whatſoever he ſhall ſay unto you. And it ſhall come to paſs, that every Soul that will not hear that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, ſhall be deſtroyed from among the People.</hi> This is he that God the Father from Heaven teſtified of, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17. 5. ſaying, <hi>This is my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Son, hear ye him:</hi> This is he that was
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:192303:28"/>
crucified and put to Death on the Croſs; and that roſe from the Dead in his Body of Fleſh and Bones, <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 39. This is he that told <hi>Mary,</hi> Joh. 20. 19. <hi>I go to my Father, and to your Father; and to my God, and your God:</hi> The Diſciples did not expect this Chriſt to come into them. But, as I promiſed before my Death and Paſſion, ſo I will ſend you the Comforter. This is he that declares he hath all Power both in Heaven and in Earth, and that gives his Commiſſion to his Diſciples, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 19. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning them to teach and publiſh all his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; and he ſaith, <hi>He that heareth you, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me; and he that heareth me, heareth him that ſent me,</hi> &amp;c. This is the Perſon denied by the Quakers to be this great Prophet, as hath been ſhewed.</p>
            <p>2. They deny the Method uſed by this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet; namely, preaching from the Scriptures, which he frequently did: <hi>Mat.</hi> 21. 42. ſaith he, <hi>Did ye never read in the Scriptures, The Stone that was ſet at naught by you Builders, the ſame is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Head of the Corner?</hi> Mat. 22. 29. <hi>Ye do err, not knowing the Scriptures.</hi> John 5. 39. <hi>Search the Scriptures,</hi> &amp;c. What was more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, than for Chriſt to preach from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and to convince his Oppoſers by them? But the Quakers deny this Method; for ſaith <hi>Lawſon</hi>'s Book, <hi>p.</hi> 14. <q>The Scriptures are not a Touch-ſtone to try Spirits withal.</q> And <hi>p.</hi> 15. he ſaith, <q>The written Law doth not convince Men of Sin.</q> And in his Book called, <hi>The untaught Teacher,</hi> p. 2, 3. he denies that the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:192303:29"/>
Miniſters of Chriſt endowed with the Spirit, ought to miniſter or preach from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>O blind Stupidity! Do they deny the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to be Chriſt's Miniſters endowed with the Spirit? And did not they preach from the Scriptures, <hi>Acts 3. 22. Peter</hi> proves Chriſt to be this Prophet from <hi>Deut.</hi> 18. 15. And <hi>Acts</hi> 8. 26, &amp;c. did not <hi>Philip</hi> preach Jeſus to the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch out of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah? Acts 18. 28. Apollos</hi> mightily convinc'd the Jews of the Truth of Jeſus being the Chriſt, out of the Scriptures. <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 11. the <hi>Bereans</hi> ſearched the Scriptures to prove <hi>Paul</hi>'s Doctrine; and <hi>Paul</hi> adviſeth <hi>Timothy</hi> to ſtudy rightly to divide the Word. Surely theſe were Miniſters en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with the Spirit.</p>
            <p>But, 3. As the Quakers do not own the Perſon, nor Method uſed and appointed by Chriſt the great Prophet; ſo they diſown the Doctrine taught by him and his Apoſtles, and like not thoſe Directions given for Doctrine: for ſay they, 'All things are to be taught and 'learned by and from the Light within; all they direct to is that. No, ſee <hi>Zech.</hi> 7. 2, 3,—7. <hi>Sherezer</hi> and <hi>Regem-melech</hi> were ſent by the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to enquire of the Prieſts and Prophets, <hi>Whether they ſhould weep in the fifth Month, ſeparating themſelves as they had done many Years before. Turn to the Light within,</hi> ſaith the Quaker; but the Lord ſpeaks by the Prophet, ſaying, <hi>Should you not hear the words which the Lord hath cried by the former Prophets?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:192303:29"/>
               <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt, who was a burning and ſhining Light, ſent two Diſciples to Jeſus, ſaying, <hi>Art thou he that ſhould come, or look do we for another?</hi> Turn to the Light within, ſaith the <hi>Quaker.</hi> But ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Go, and tell</hi> John <hi>the things ye have both ſeen and heard,</hi> &amp;c. Such outward Means were returned by Chriſt, the true Prophet and Light of the World, for <hi>John</hi>'s Satisfaction, <hi>Luke</hi> 7. 19, 22.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luke</hi> 3. 10,—14. The People came to <hi>Jeſus,</hi> ſaying, <hi>What ſhall we do?</hi> Alſo the Publicans, ſaying, <hi>What ſhall we do? And the Souldiers ſaid, What ſhall we do?</hi> Turn to the Light within, ſaith the <hi>Quaker.</hi> But ſaith <hi>Jeſus,</hi> who had another Spirit; <hi>He that hath two Coats, let him impart one to him that hath none: Exact no more,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Do Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to none, Accuſe no Man falſely, Be content with your Wages.</hi> Mat. 19. 16,—21. a certain young Man came to Chriſt, ſaying, <hi>What good thing ſhall I do that I may inherit Eternal Life?</hi> Turn to the Light within, ſaith the <hi>Quaker:</hi> But ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Keep the Commandments, and ſell what thou haſt, and give to the Poor, and thou ſhalt have Treaſure in Heaven,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Joh. 6. 28, 29. the Jews demanded of Chriſt, ſaying, <hi>What ſhall we do that we may work the Work of God?</hi> Turn to the Light within, ſaith the <hi>Quaker.</hi> But ſaith Chriſt, this is the Work of God, <hi>That ye believe in his Son,</hi> that is, in me that talk with you, that came into the World to die for you. <hi>Lord, what wilt thou have me to do?</hi> ſaith <hi>Saul;</hi> Turn to the Light within, ſaith the <hi>Quaker. Acts</hi> 9. 6. ſaith the Lord
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:192303:30"/>
Chriſt, <hi>Go into the City, and it ſhall be told thee.</hi> Acts 22. 10-16. <hi>Ariſe, and go to</hi> Damaſcus, <hi>and there it ſhall be told thee, of all things that are appointed for thee to do:</hi> And that not by a Light within, for <hi>Ananias</hi> was to inſtruct him into the Will of Chriſt the great Prophet. So <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 37, 38. The poor Jews, <hi>pricked in the Heart, cried out, Men and Brethren, what ſhall we do?</hi> Turn to the Light within, ſaith the Quaker. But ſaith <hi>Peter,</hi> one that had the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and be baptized, for the Remiſſion of Sins,</hi> &amp;c. I might weary you with ſhewing how the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers oppoſe the Teachings of Chriſt's Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Office.</p>
            <p>And that the Quakers deny the Prophetick Office of Chriſt, it appears by their denying his Goſpel-Ordinances; and this brings me to the Sixth Head, as I obſerve in their Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet.</p>
            <p>VI. <hi>and Laſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which they would inſinuate to the World, <q>That they believe, and are fully perſwaded, that Baptiſm which is eſſential to Salvation, or Chriſtianity, or the Laver, without which none can be true Chriſtians, or ſaved, is the inward or ſpiritual waſhing of Regeneration by the Word of Life. This is the ſaving Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm into Chriſt and his Church, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth <hi>the anſwer of a good Conſcience towards God,</hi> of which the outward was a Figure, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 21. This is that one Baptiſm of Chriſt, by one Spirit, into that one Body whereof
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:192303:30"/>
Chriſt is Head.</q> And then, that they may not appear with open Face, but under a Mask, in ſtriking at Chriſt's Ordinance, but ſtill with the ſame Deſign, they alter the ſtroak ſeemingly, and go on; <q>As for Dipping, or Sprinkling Infants or young Children, we find no Precept or Precedent in Holy Scripture for the practice thereof; and therefore we cannot think our not believing it, eſſential or neceſſary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, or making Chriſtians, a ſufficient Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to prove us no Chriſtians, unleſs it can be proved that none are ſaved without it, and that all are ſaved that have it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The ſcope and medium of this Article, is to make null and aboliſh the ſacred Ordinance of Water-Baptiſm: And as to what they ſay, that their not believing Sprinkling or Dipping of young Children to be eſſential to Salvation, or making Chriſtians, can be no ſufficient Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to prove them no Chriſtians. No certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I believe that no Advocate for that Cauſe could do it from thoſe Premiſes.</p>
            <p>I ſhall proceed to examine their Sentiments touching that Sacred Ordinance of Water-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm; and it appears that they deny thoſe two great Ordinances inſtituted by our Lord and great Prophet, namely, Baptiſm in Water, and the Supper adminiſtred in Bread and Wine; then one good Argument, amongſt many, may be drawn from thence to prove the Quakers no Chriſtians. Let us therefore have recourſe to their Conſtruing Books, and ſee what they ſay.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:192303:31"/>
               <hi>Pernell's Shield of the Truth,</hi> p. 11. <q>The Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm. we own, is the Baptiſm of Chriſt with the Holy Ghoſt and with Fire, but we deny all other.</q> See <hi>p.</hi> 12. Here the Quakers fully deny Water-Baptiſm. See alſo <hi>James Nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor's Salutation to the Seed of God,</hi> p. 33, 34. where he ſlights and denies Baptiſm in Water, calling it a <hi>carnal thing.</hi> But <hi>Edw. Burroughs,</hi> with open Face, and great Confidence, teſtifies againſt Chriſt's Ordinances being now in force; <q>I do affirm, ſaith he, that Circumciſion is as much in force as Water-Baptiſm; and the Pafchal Lamb, as the Bread and Wine; for the continuing of them would have been a Judaizing of the Evangelical Worſhip: To aſſert their continuance, would be as much as in ſuch lies to pluck up the Goſpel, or Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Worſhip, by the Roots. Hence that Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation, Ordinances of Chriſt, I do renounce as unſcriptural and unevangelical, and can teſtify, from the ſame Spirit by which <hi>Paul</hi> renounced Circumciſion, that they are to be rejected.</q> 
               <hi>Burroughs</hi>'s Works, <hi>pag.</hi> 108, 109. Here is a compound of Ignorance and Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with a witneſs; becauſe Chriſt put an end to Circumciſion and other Ceremonies of the Law, as <hi>Paul</hi> teaches; therefore by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Deluſion, and groſs Ignorance in the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, <hi>E. B.</hi> will renounce and put an end to Chriſt's Ordinances. Surely theſe Men have learned to put Darkneſs for Light, and Light for Darkneſs; for what can be a more effectual way to pluck up Goſpel-Worſhip by the Roots,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:192303:31"/>
than to make null and renounce Goſpel-Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances? But the wickedneſs of this deluded Man lies chiefly in patronizing his notorious Falſhoods to the ſame Spirit that <hi>Paul</hi> had, which was the Spirit of Chriſt: What is this but blaſpheming the Holy Spirit? See <hi>Pernell's Shield of the Truth,</hi> p. 12. where he calls Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Baptiſm, <q>A formal Invention and Imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Men, and ſo a meer Deluſion.</q> 
               <hi>Smith</hi> the Quaker's <hi>Primmer,</hi> pag. 39. <q>Thy Baptiſm, Bread and Wine, roſe from the Pope's Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall only bring in the Verdict of <hi>Robert Ruckhill;</hi> ſee Mr. <hi>Grantham's Chriſtianiſmus Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitivus,</hi> Book 4. Treat. 11. See how <hi>Ruckhill</hi> condemns the Baptized Churches, for keeping the Ordinances of Chriſt as they were deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to the Saints, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>O ungrateful Men, ſaith he, unworthy, till you repent and loath your ſelves, the Name of Chriſtians; hath the afflicted perſecuted Church been. baniſhed into the Wilderneſs for many hundred Years; and now at her return, when ſhe is expecting a far more exceeding and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal weight of Glory, both Inward and Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, which her great Afflictions have wrought for her; will you now, I ſay, allow her no better Ornaments, but theſe very ſame ſhe wore 1600 Years ago? which alſo for many hundred Years have been revelled in, and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily polluted by that naſty Whore of <hi>Babylon.</hi> Poor Bride, muſt ſhe now put on thoſe old Clothes and rotten Rags again? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Will
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:192303:32"/>
you deny this beautiful Bride, the Lamb's Wife, that Priviledg your own Wives will ſcorn to be denied by you? O how weak are your Hearts, ſaith the Lord God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>To which great and ſwelling words of Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Mr. <hi>Grantham</hi> gives a full and pathetical Anſwer.</p>
            <p>But from all this you may obſerve, that as <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphirah</hi> agreed to lie againſt the Holy Ghoſt, ſo theſe againſt the Ordinances of Chriſt. But the miſery of it is, altho their Deſign is the Death of the Object, yet as the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the two Elders againſt <hi>Suſannah,</hi> and the falſe Witneſſes againſt Chriſt, they cannot agree in their Teſtimony againſt the Goſpel-Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances.</p>
            <p>For ſaith <hi>Smith's Primmer,</hi> p. 39. <q>Thy Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, Bread and Wine, roſe from the Pope's Inventions.</q> So ſaith <hi>Higgins's Warning,</hi> p. 5. But <hi>Ruckhill</hi> ſaith, <q>They were the Churches Ornaments 1600 Years ago.</q> This he plainly confeſſeth; Now either the former, or the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of theſe inſpired Men, with all their Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility, are infallibly Liars; for if they were the Churches Ornaments 1600 Years ago, as <hi>Ruckhill</hi> confeſſeth, then they were not invented by the Pope, as <hi>Smith</hi> and <hi>Higgins</hi> pretend, there being no Pope of that Antiquity. So that I muſt leave you to clear your ſelves if you can tell how.</p>
            <p>I proceed to examine <hi>R. Ruckhill's</hi> great and empty flouriſh, and ſwelling words of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:192303:32"/>1. Here <hi>R. Ruckhill</hi> pretends much skill in the time of the Churches going into, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning out of the Wilderneſs: But I ſuppoſe, were he asked, What this Wilderneſs is, and the exact Time when the Church went in and came out of it? he would give but a bewildered Anſwer.</p>
            <p>2. It appears from hence, as I have before ſhewed, that the Quakers believe the Eternal weight of Glory, both inward and outward, is to be received by the Church at her return out of the Wilderneſs, and enjoyed here on this ſide the Grave in this mortal State.</p>
            <p>3. Here <hi>R. Ruckhill</hi> is forced to confeſs, that the Ordinances of Chriſt were the Churches Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments 1600 Years ago; but now they are a great diſhonour and deformity to her, therefore he diſdainfully calls them <hi>old rotten Rags;</hi> as though 1600 Years were time enough to rot all the Ordinances of Chriſt, and wear them out to Rags.</p>
            <p>4. He diſdains theſe Ordinances, becauſe the Whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> hath revelled in them, and polluted them.</p>
            <p>But for all <hi>R. Ruckhill's</hi> skill in the Churches Apparel, there were alſo other Ornaments, as the Belief of the Scriptures, Faith, Holineſs, Love, Charity and Patience, Mercy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now have not all theſe been corrupted and abuſed by the Whore of <hi>Babylon?</hi> and counterfeit Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, counterfeit Scriptures, counterfeit and feigned Faith, Holineſs, Love, Charity, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and Mercy, ſet up in the room thereof?
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:192303:33"/>
doth it therefore follow, that all theſe Vertues muſt be thrown away, becauſe the Whore hath polluted them? No ſurely, the Quakers will not ſay ſo, nor account Prayer, Preaching, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> old rotten Rags, becauſe the Whore hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled in them.</p>
            <p>Was the Ark of God ever the worſe for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining ſome time in the Houſe of <hi>Dagon? Iſrael</hi> were ſometimes a long ſpace without the true Law, true Worſhip, and true God, being involved in Idolatry and Darkneſs, yet both <hi>Aſah</hi> and <hi>Hezekiah</hi> were for returning to the true God, and true Worſhip, when that Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was diſperſed, 2 <hi>Chron. 15. 3. 2 Chron.</hi> 30. 5. Even ſo now the Lord having diſperſed that Fog of Popiſh Darkneſs; may not <hi>R. Ruckhill</hi>'s Lamentation be taken up againſt the Quakers and others? O ungrateful Men, hath God di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſed theſe Clouds of Popiſh Darkneſs, and diſcovered his Laws and Ordinances in their Primitive Purity, and will you now reject and contemn them as old rotten Rags, and rebel againſt the Light? But <hi>R. Ruckhill</hi> would now by all means have the Church to have a new Coat, her old Ornaments being worn to Rags. And <hi>R. Ruckhill</hi> muſt needs have the Church to have new Ordinances, as often as Mens Wives have new Clothes, or elſe ſhe muſt go naked.</p>
            <p>But, ſaith <hi>Robert Ruckhill,</hi> in the foremention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Diſcourſe, <q>We do not deny Baptiſm, or any other Ordinance, when the Spirit of the Lord leadeth to them.</q> It's but fair to conclude, that the Quakers have not the Leadings of the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:192303:33"/>
Spirit of God to guide them into this Goſpel-Ordinance. But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R. Ruckhill</hi> would recal this again, ſaying, <q>It hath appeared, that the Spirit of the Lord leads forward, not backward; upward, not downward, (and then he preſumes to ſay) elſe the Spirit may as well lead into Judaiſm, as into the Ordinances aforeſaid.</q> What pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Ignorance and groſs Darkneſs is here, to imagine that the Spirit of Chriſt, promiſed, <hi>John</hi> 14. 26. &amp; 16. 31. to guide into all Truth, and to bring to remembrance the Doctrine Chriſt had taught, might as well lead them into Judaiſm, which Chriſt had and came to aboliſh, by <hi>R. Ruckhill</hi>'s Argument? When <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanias</hi> is ſent to <hi>Paul,</hi> compare <hi>Acts 9. 17, 18. Act. 22. 16 that he may receive his ſight, and be filled with the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> he ſaid, <hi>And now why tarrieſt thou? Ariſe and be Baptized.</hi> Might not <hi>Paul</hi> have ſaid, I am filled with the Holy Ghoſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, What, muſt I go back to the Shadow, to ſuch a carnal thing as Water-Baptiſm? But <hi>Paul</hi> had the Spirit of God, and not of the Quakers, and therefore he readily ſubmitted to this Holy Ordinance, and ſtands not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with Fleſh and Blood. See alſo <hi>Acts</hi> 10. from 44, to 48. While <hi>Peter</hi> was preaching the Goſpel to <hi>Cornelius,</hi> and thoſe with him, <hi>the Holy Ghoſt fell on all them that heard the Word;</hi> and <hi>they heard them ſpeak with Tongues, and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified God. Then anſwered</hi> Peter, <hi>Can any for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid Water, that theſe ſhould not be baptized who have received the Holy Ghoſt as well as we?</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:192303:34"/>
Doubtleſs had <hi>R. Ruckhill,</hi> or any of the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers been there, had there been any ſuch a Creature in thoſe Days, they would have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid Water, and told <hi>Peter,</hi> he was miſtaken; Hold, <hi>Peter,</hi> they have the Subſtance, the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm of the Spirit, wilt thou lead them back to the Letter, to the carnal Thing of Water-Baptiſm? If <hi>G. Fox</hi> had been there with his Book, <hi>The Great Myſtery,</hi> pag. 65. he would out of that have proved to <hi>Peter,</hi> that <hi>Paul</hi> told of the Spirit's Baptiſm, and brought the Saints off from Things that are ſeen; and Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is ſeen, and its Baptiſm; from that Text 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 18. Would any Man in his Senſes have drawn ſuch an Inference? But it is a lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thing, that theſe Men care not for the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, except it be to abuſe them. But to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, <hi>Verſ. 48. Peter</hi> being of another mind, having another Spirit than the Quakers, <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to be baptized in the Name of the Lord.</hi> From whence I groundedly conclude, That the higheſt Attainments, or greateſt Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the Holy Spirit, do not exempt or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe Men from, but fit them for Goſpel-Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances. But I have ſhewed you before, it is the Baptiſm of the Spirit, and no other, that they will allow.</p>
            <p>This is that they contend for in their Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet; they ſay, <q>The Baptiſm of Water was put an End to at Chriſt's Death; and then that of the Spirit ſucceeds, of which that of Water was a Type.</q> This is their common Opinion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:192303:34"/>To which I anſwer, That it was Water-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm that Chriſt gave in Commiſſion to his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to Adminiſter, after he was riſen from the Dead, <hi>Mat. 28. Mark</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt;</hi> They were not to adminiſter that of Sufferings; his Diſciples nor Apoſtles were not to perſecute, nor lay Sufferings upon others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly;</hi> If they ſay that the Apoſtles were to baptize with the Spirit, as ſome of them want no Ignorance or Confidence to affirm.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt;</hi> I demand, Whether the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that were not peculiar to Chriſt, <hi>Mat. 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 11. He,</hi> meaning Chriſt, <hi>ſhall baptize you with the Holy Ghoſt, and with Fire?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly;</hi> Whether that if the Command, <hi>Mat. 28. 18. Mark</hi> 16. 16. be to command the Apoſtles to baptize with the Holy Ghoſt, and Fire? If it were, I demand when and where they obeyed it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly;</hi> Whether we may not groundedly believe, That the baptizing Men and Women in Water, in the Name of Chriſt, which the Apoſtles did, was not in obedience to ſome Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from the Lord ſo to do?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly;</hi> Let the Quakers ſhew when and where the Lord gave them command ſo to do, if this of <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. and <hi>Mark</hi> 16. was not it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly;</hi> If <hi>Peter</hi> had not Authority from the Lord to baptize with Water, <hi>Acts</hi> 10. latter end, I demand whether you do not conclude he finned in ſo doing? for he commanded them to be baptized in the Name of the Lord; ſee
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:192303:35"/>
               <hi>Deut. 18. 20. But the Prophet that ſhall preſume to ſpeak a word in my Name, that I have not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, that Prophet ſhall die, ſaith the Lord.</hi> I wiſh this were ſeriouſly weighed by all that counterfeit Chriſt's Ordinances.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly;</hi> That whereas it is alledged that Baptiſm may be done, or left undone, that it is a thing indifferent: Then I demand, whether it was not as great a Sin in <hi>Peter, Acts</hi> 10. 48. to command them to be baptized, as it was in thoſe, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 2, 3. who command to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from Meats, and forbid to marry, which are things left at liberty? For to command to do what God hath left at liberty, to do or not to do, is equally a Sin to the ſame extent, with forbidding what God hath left to Mens liberty: Therefore I would have none to count the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Chriſt Things indifferent. Let what hath been ſaid be conſidered. But the Apoſtles in purſuance of the aforeſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 18, 19, 20. <hi>Mark</hi> 16. 16. did preach and baptize with Water; that being the only Baptiſm they were to adminiſter. That of Sufferings by Perſecution being from the Devil and wicked Men; that of the Spirit being peculiar from Chriſt, and that of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by his Apoſtles and Diſciples. And thus according to the Commiſſion of their Lord, you find them adminiſtring, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 38. and reaching; <hi>Repent and be baptized for Remiſſion of Sins, and ye ſhall receive the Gift of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Acts 8. 12. <hi>When they believed</hi> Philip, <hi>preaching the things concerning the Kingdom of
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:192303:35"/>
God, and Name of Jeſus, they were baptized both Men and Women.</hi> Ver. 36, 37. ſaith the Eunuch, <hi>See, here is Water, what doth hinder me to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized?</hi> Philip <hi>anſwered, If thou believe with all thy Heart, it is lawful for thee;</hi> as moſt truly read. And they went down into, and came up out of the Water, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Acts 10. 47, 48. <hi>And he commanded them. to be baptized in the Name of the Lord;</hi> and none could forbid Water, tho they were baptized with the Spirit before. So that altho the pouring forth of the extraordinary Gifts of the Spirit are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratively called a Baptiſm; and the Greatneſs and Over-whelmings of Chriſt's Sufferings are ſo called comparatively: Yet there is but one Baptiſm in a full and proper ſenſe, and that is that of Water, in which the penitent Believer is buried, <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2. 12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 4. And what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Quakers pretend, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 5. Chriſt is that one Lord; and to believe in him, his Offices and Doctrine, is this one Faith, and to be baptized in Water is the one Baptiſm; and how ridiculouſly they abuſe that Text in their Pamphlet, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 21. In <hi>ver.</hi> 21. he ſpeaks of God's Patience in waiting upon the old World <hi>while the Ark was a preparing, wherein eight Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were ſaved by Water: The like Figure where unto, even Baptiſm, doth alſo now ſave us; not the putting away of the Filth of the Fleſh,</hi> that is, not the end of Water-Baptiſm, to cleanſe the Filth from the outward Man, as were the many Waſhings under the Law; <hi>but it is the anſwer of a good Conſcience towards God;</hi> in ſhewing
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:192303:36"/>
your Obedience to his Law, as it is ſaid, <hi>Luke</hi> 7. 30. <hi>The Phariſees and Lawyers rejected the Counſel of God againſt themſelves, in not being baptized of him;</hi> and ſo contracted Guilt to their Conſciences. And their ſaying, Water-Baptiſm was a Figure of the Spiritual, is an apparent Falſhood, the Text under debate hath no ſuch meaning: But thus, as eight Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons believed in the Lord's preaching, by the Ark's building, when the old World was threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, they got into this Ark, when the unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving World mocked at it; the Water bears up the Ark, and thoſe in it, and ſaves them whilſt the others were deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>So the Threats of periſhing eternally are pronounced in the Goſpel againſt Sinners. Now the penitent Believer puts on Chriſt by Water-Baptiſm, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 27. which is the initiating and ingrafting Ordinance; and I demand of the Quakers, if they can, to prove where Water-Baptiſm is called a Figure of the Spiritual; and alſo to ſhew me from the Scriptures where any were commanded to obſerve the Figure, when at the ſame time they enjoy the Subſtance. But <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Cornclius,</hi> and others had the Spiritual Baptiſm, and yet were commanded to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized with Water.</p>
            <p>Another impertinency in their Pamphlet is, they ſay, they cannot believe dipping or ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Infants, unleſs it can be proved that none are ſaved without it, and all are ſaved that have it. They ſeem here moſt directly to ſtrike at Infant-Baptiſm; but their deſign is to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:192303:36"/>
root out that ſacred Ordinance of Chriſt, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers Baptiſm: And therefore I demand, whether the Quakers believe, that all that are baptized with the Spirit, as they count it, tho a Spirit of Deluſion, ſhall infallibly be ſaved? if they ſay they do, then what is the Reaſon they own or believe falling away, and going from the Light? and why do ſo many turn wet Quakers, and become as vile in their Lives, as they are in their Principles? But if they do not own an Infallibility of being ſaved by that Spirit's Baptiſm they pretend to, then what is in theſe words? And to conclude this Head, I would not have the Quakers pretend to be baptized with the holy Spirit, till they believe in Chriſt, and obey his Appointments; for <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 32. he gives his holy Spirit to them that obey him. To conclude this, let all that would be Chriſt's Diſciples, learn of him that hath led in the way of Righteouſneſs, when by Faith and Repentance you have laid hold on Chriſt, O delay not to put him on by Baptiſm! and ſo you will become viſible Members of his Myſtical Body, be Heirs of the Promiſe of the holy Spirit, and other bleſſed Priviledges, as a Right to the Lord's Table to ſup with him in this Kingdom of Grace, and dwell with him in Glory hereafter.</p>
            <p>2. The Quakers in their Pamphlet, in like manner with Falſhoods and Impertinencies e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade the Supper of the Lord inſtituted and adminiſtred in Bread and Wine. Say they, <q>The Supper of the Lord we own and tenderly
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:192303:37"/>
conſider in a twofold ſenſe. <hi>Firſt,</hi> In the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure: <hi>Secondly,</hi> In the Subſtance. 1. That our Lord Jeſus Chriſt at his Supper with his Diſciples did eat the Paſſeover, which was for the fulfilling and Conſummation of the Feaſts under the Law, <hi>Luke</hi> 22. and at his Supper he did take and miniſter the Bread and the Cup to his Diſciples (for there was no Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation) ſaying, <hi>This do in remembrance of me;</hi> and ſaith the Lord, <hi>As often as ye eat this Bread, and drink this Cup, ye do ſhew forth the Lord's Death till he come;</hi> 1 Cor. 11. After this they did more clearly know his Coming, and Chriſt after the Spirit, Jeſus Chriſt in them,</q> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 5, &amp;c. The Reader may ſee with what deceivable words theſe Impoſtors go about to evade and make null the Ordinance of the Lord's-Supper adminiſtred in Bread and Wine.</p>
            <p>But before I come to anſwer their imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Evaſions and manifold Corruptions of the Scriptures, I ſhall ſhew you that they plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deny the Supper of the Lord adminiſtred in Bread and Wine, to be now a ſtanding Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance in the Church of Chriſt, and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable by Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Let us hear them ſpeak out more plainly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we anſwer them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Parnell</hi>'s <hi>Shield of the Truth,</hi> p. 13. <q>Feeding upon Husks and Shadows that are carnal, for the Bread which the World (that is, all that are not Quakers) eat, is natural and carnal; ſo alſo is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> which they drink, and there is no Communion but natural, outward and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:192303:37"/>
carnal. <hi>Smith</hi>'s <hi>Primmer,</hi> p. 39. Thy Bread and Wine in the Lord's Supper are the Popes Invention.</q> See how bare-fac'dly they can lie againſt the Truth. See <hi>Nailor's Love to the Loſt,</hi> p. 56. <q>Which all know who are come to his Supper, where the Father and Son are come in and ſup with the Creature, which all the Imitators and Obſervers of Times are ignorant of, whoſe Contention is about out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, Let us have the Teſtimony of <hi>George Fox</hi> le-Grand, <hi>Great Myſtery,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 16. ſays he, <q>Chriſt has triumphed over the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and blotted them out, and they are not to be touched; and the Saints have Chriſt in them, who is the end of outward Forms: and thou art deceived who thinkeſt to find the Living amongſt the Dead.</q> You ſee by this how miſerably theſe Men abuſe the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Now it appears by all this, that either the Apoſtles were ignorant about the nature and manner of Chriſt's ſecond Coming, or elſe the Quakers are greatly deluded in ſaying, he is come the ſecond time already. But to clear the Apoſtles and Primitive Saints from that Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance the Quakers caſt upon them, and to make it appear that they did not believe the giving of the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. to be the ſecond Coming of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>1. Becauſe the Apoſtles are found in the adminiſtring, and the Primitive Chriſtians in partaking of this Ordinance, after the Holy
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:192303:38"/>
Spirit that Chriſt promiſed to ſend, was come, as hath been before ſaid of Baptiſm. This ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears from <hi>Acts 2. 42, 46. They continued ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt in the Apoſtles Doctrine and Fellowſhip, in breaking of Bread, and Prayer.</hi> Acts 20. 7. <hi>The Diſciples came together to break Bread.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All Expoſitors that I know of conclude, this was to celebrate the Ordinance of the Lord's-Supper; ſee this fully manifeſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 1, 2. compared with Verſe 23, to the <hi>29th</hi> at large; <hi>Be ye followers of me, even as I alſo am of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Montanus,</hi> an approved Interpreter, reads it thus, <hi>Imitatores mei <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtote, ſicut &amp; ego Chriſti:</hi> Be ye Imitators of me, as I am of Chriſt. <hi>Now I praiſe you, Brethren, that you remember me in all things, and keep the Ordinances, as I delivered them unto you.</hi> Ver. 23. <hi>For I have received of the Lord that which I delivered unto you.</hi> As if he had ſaid, thoſe Ordinances that I praiſe you for the keeping of, are the ſame that I received of the Lord: And this is one, that the Lord Jeſus <hi>the ſame Night in which he was betrayed, took Bread; bleſſed it, and brake it,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now if the Quakers were not ſtark blind, or wilfully ignorant, would they conclude that <hi>Paul</hi> and the Primitive Saints did not know that Chriſt was come in Spirit? or, that the Promiſe of the Holy Ghoſt was given? So he goes on and tells them, <hi>ver. 26. As often as ye eat this Bread, and drink this Cup, ye ſhew forth the Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s Death till he come.</hi> So that the giving forth of the Spirit was not the ſecond coming of Chriſt, as the Quakers dream; for how im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:192303:38"/>
were it for to celebrate an Ordinance in remembrance of him that was within them, I leave to the Reader to judg.</p>
            <p>2. Chriſt is not come, becauſe that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is not come that Chriſt ſpeaks of; <hi>I will not henceforth drink of the Fruit of the Vine, till I drink it new with you in my Father's Kingdom;</hi> notwithſtanding the Quakers do ſo abuſe that Saying of our Lord. For it is the Duty of the Diſciples of Chriſt to pray for the coming of that Kingdom; and it is moſt evident, that the Will of God is not done upon Earth, as it is in Heaven; for the greateſt part of the World live in Diſobedience to the Will of God: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth Chriſt now drink of the Fruit of the Vine with his Diſciples, becauſe he is at his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Right-hand in the glorious Heavens: and his Diſciples upon Earth are to break and eat Bread, and drink of the Fruit of the Vine till he come, in remembrance of his broken Body, and Blood ſhed for their Redemption and Salvation; in which Chriſt hath ſpiritual Communion with them, not perſonal, which he will have after his ſecond Coming. And,</p>
            <p>3. <hi>Paul</hi> and the Primitive Chriſtians did not believe the givings forth of the Spirit, to be the ſecond coming of Chriſt, becauſe they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved and expected him to come in a perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, glorious and viſible manner; <hi>Phil. 3. 20. We look for the Saviour, who ſhall change our vile Bodies, and make them like his own glorious Body:</hi> that being one thing that will be done at
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:192303:39"/>
Chriſt's ſecond Coming. And <hi>Paul</hi> and the Chriſtians did look for Chriſt's ſecond and perſonal Coming, becauſe they were told, <hi>Acts</hi> 1. 11. That <hi>the ſame Jeſus ſhould come in like manner</hi> (viſible in his Body of Fleſh and Bones) <hi>as he did aſcend,</hi> as hath been before proved more largely; and as Chriſt himſelf ſhewed his Diſciples, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. at large, that <hi>his coming ſhould be glorious and viſible;</hi> Rev. 1. 7. Long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Spirit or Comforter was come, faith <hi>John, Behold, he cometh, every Eye ſhall ſee him; and they that pierced him, ſhall mourn.</hi> 1 Theſſ. 4. 6. <hi>For the Lord himſelf ſhall deſcend from Heaven with a ſhout, with the Voice of the Arch-Angel, and the Trump of God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>4. If the Quakers will need have this to be true, which no Chriſtians can allow them, that Chriſt is come the ſecond time, as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures have foretold of him, and as he himſelf ſaid he would; and from thence they conclude that Baptiſm and the Supper of the Lord are at an end; I would know whether all other Goſpel-Ordinances are not at an end alſo, as Preaching, Prayer, Acts of Mercy and Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the like? And if ſo, why do the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers pretend to Preach and Pray? for in that Kingdom there is no need to teach any to know the Lord; no need of Prayer, for then the Saints poſſeſs the fulleſt Enjoyments they can pray or wiſh for; they ſhall hunger no more, and ſo have no need of Alms; and in that Kingdom, they <hi>neither marry, nor are given in
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:192303:39"/>
Marriage; neither can they die any more,</hi> Luke 20. 35, 36. But the Quakers pretend to Preach, and Pray, and give Alms; they Marry, and they Die. See then what horrid Contradictions and groſs Abſurdities attend this Spirit of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion. And to what End they bring 1 <hi>Cor. 10. 15, 16, 17. Rev. 3. 20. Prov.</hi> 9. 4, 5. with <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. I know not, except to abuſe the Scriptures, or confute themſelves. All Chriſtians own Chriſt to be the Bread of Life, and have ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Communion with him in his Ordinances; which ſpiritual Communion they cannot have, whatever they pretend, who do not obey Chriſt in his Ordinances, but flight, vilify, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn the ſame, as the Quakers do. But thoſe that open when he knocks, by the Hammer of his Word; thoſe that receive his Word, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances and Appointments, he will come into them by his Spirit; and having Communion one with another, as one Bread, ſo their Fellowſhip ſhall be with the Father and the Son ſpiritually, and ſo he hath promiſed to be with his Church in the participation of his Ordinances to the end of the World? And though we highly own and honour the Ordinances of Chriſt; yet as we believe thoſe that reject and deſpiſe them, whatever they pretend, have no ſpiritual Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Chriſt: ſo alſo thoſe that are not duly fitted and prepared for them, may not expect any Benefit or Advantage by them.</p>
            <p>In the next place, they talk of the Seals of the New Covenant: Which term, in the plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:192303:40"/>
I deny; and believe, that the Spirit, or Holy Ghoſt, thoſe Meaſures or Gifts thereof that God beſtows upon Chriſtians, is the Seal of their Acceptance with him; as <hi>Epheſ. 1. 13. After ye believed, ye were ſealed with the Holy Spirit of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Whoever accounts theſe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Ordinances the Seals of the Covenant, are ſo far miſtaken, for they are part of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant it ſelf. Saith Chriſt, <hi>If ye love me, keep my Commandments; and I will pray the Father, and he ſhall give you another Comforter, that ſhall abide with you for ever, even the Spirit of Truth.</hi> This Spirit which is promiſed as a Seal, is upon the Terms of keeping Chriſt's Commandments, of which are Baptiſm, and the Lord's Supper. <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 32. He gives this Seal of the Spirit to thoſe that obey him, duly obſerving and obeying Chriſt's Ordinances and Commands, from a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Faith in his Word and Promiſes, as well as in his Death, Blood, and Merits; and alſo to attend this. Goſpel Faith with a pious Life; and ſo reſigning up our ſelves to be Chriſt's, he hath promiſed us the Seal of his Spirit, as an earneſt of our Inheritance, which is hereafter to be enjoyed.</p>
            <p>But vainly do the Quakers feed themſelves with Wind, in imagining that they have the Holy Spirit, or Seal of this new Covenant, who rebel againſt Chriſt the Miniſter of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, condemn his Blood, deſpiſe his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So that from hence it appears, they have nothing to do to take his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:192303:40"/>
into their Mouths, ſeeing they hate to be reformed.</p>
            <p>And as for their next Impertinency, in talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of one outward Type or Shadow, being a Type of another outward Type; I am an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate for no ſuch Notion, neither do I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that Circumciſion was a Type of Baptiſm, but of the Circumciſion of the Heart; nor that the Paſſover was a Type of the Lord's Supper, but of Chriſt the true Paſchal Lamb, ſlain for the Sins of the World.</p>
            <p>And now to conclude, Let all Chriſtians ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the Grace of Chriſt, who gave his Body to be broken, and his Blood to be ſhed; and not only ſo, but in love to his People, hath left this Ordinance of his Supper in his laſt Will and Teſtament, to be celebrated, he before know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Frailties, we being ſubject to forget his Kindneſs. Let us therefore obſerve it, with the reſt of his Ordinances; and <hi>bleſſed is the Servant whom the Lord when he cometh ſhall find ſo doing.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:192303:41"/>
            <head>A POSTSCRIPT TO THE QUAKERS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIRS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>You cannot be ignorant, that thoſe two great Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, (<hi>viz.</hi>) The Reſurrection of the dead Bodies of Men from the Graves of the Earth, and Eternal Judgment, are believed as two Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the Chriſtian Faith, wherein your Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief hath been queſtioned, and you profeſs your Belief in neither of them in your Paper.</p>
            <p>But the contrary hath been manifeſted by your own Tongues and Pens; for <hi>Tho. Lawſon,</hi> and <hi>John Slee,</hi> both Quakers, gave <hi>William Jef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey</hi> a Paper, under their own Hands, wherein was aſſerted, <hi>That nothing of Man that goes into the Grave, ſhall riſe again;</hi> and one of your Friends with whom I was reaſoning upon this Subject, asked me, <hi>If, I were ſo ignorant as to believe that Bulk</hi> (pointing at my Body) <hi>ſhould riſe again
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:192303:41"/>
from the Grave?</hi> But upon occaſion you will ſay, You believe the Reſurrection of the Body; pray then, what doth your Friend <hi>Turner</hi> intend by theſe Arguments?</p>
            <p>1. <q>If the Bodies of Men riſe again; then there is a preheminence in the Bodies of Men above the Bodies of Beaſts, which is to give <hi>Solomon</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3. 19. 2. If the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of Men ſhall riſe again, this is to give <hi>Job</hi> the Lie, who ſaith, <hi>The Eye that ſees me, ſhall ſee me no more,</hi> Job 7. 8.</q> 3. <hi>Fleſh and Blood ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God,</hi> (who can ſuppoſe any other, than that the import of theſe Arguments is, to deny the Reſurrection of the Body?) ſee Mr. <hi>Hicks</hi>'s <hi>Dialogue,</hi> p. 56.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, That the Conſequence of neither of theſe Arguments follows from the Premiſes: for where <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Man hath no preheminence above a Beaſt;</hi> he ſhews in what reſpect he means, <hi>verſ. 20. All are of the Duſt, and all turn to Duſt again;</hi> in this ſenſe all go to one Place, and ſo Man hath no prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence. But in Point of the Reſurrection he hath, for a way is deviſed, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14. 14. That <hi>Man ſhall not for ever be expelled from God.</hi> And a Promiſe is made, <hi>Hoſ. 13. 14. I will ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom them from the Power of the Grave; I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem them from Death; for Death and Hell,</hi> (or, ſaith your Margin, <hi>the Grave) ſhall deliver up the dead,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. 13. And it is true, the Eye that ſaw <hi>Job,</hi> ſhould ſee him no more, not in this mortal State. But ſee <hi>Job 19. 25, 26, 27. For I know that my Redeemer liveth, and that he
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:192303:42"/>
ſhall ſtand at the latter day upon the Earth. And altho after my Skin, Worms deſtroy my Body, yet in my Fleſh ſhall I ſee God: Whom I ſhall ſee for my ſelf, and not another: Mine Eyes ſhall behold him, tho my Reins be conſumed within me.</hi> What is more manifeſt than that <hi>Job</hi> did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in the Reſurrection? After Worms had deſtroyed his Body, yet in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he ſhould ſee his Redeemer; Where? upon the Earth: when? at the laſt, or latter Day.</p>
            <p>3. His Argument from 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 50. is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploded; the Argument is, <hi>Fleſh and Blood cannot inherit the Kingdom of God.</hi> To which I anſwer:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1ſt,</hi> Then let your Friend <hi>Tho. Lawſon</hi> be aſhamed of what he ſaith in his Book, <hi>p.</hi> 9, and 19. where he affirms himſelf and Friends to be now in Poſſeſſion of the Kingdom of God aforeſaid, and to have Eternal Life really in Poſſeſſion: Do you believe <hi>Tho. Lawſon,</hi> or any of you now living, are not made of Fleſh, Blood and Bones.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly,</hi> We own, that <hi>Fleſh and Blood cannot inherit the Kingdom of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt;</hi> Under a twofold Acceptation of the Word.</p>
            <p>1. Not carnal, ſenſual and unregenerate Men; for <hi>John 3. 3,—8. Except a Man be born again, he cannot ſee the Kingdom of God. That which is born of the Fleſh, is Fleſh,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Marvel not that I ſaid unto thee Ye muſt be born again,</hi> (or, <hi>from above,</hi> ſaith your Margent). The carnal, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate Man is ſaid to be in the Fleſh, and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:192303:42"/>
not ſubject to the Law of God, neither indeed can be in that State: So that to be <hi>carnally or fleſhly-minded is Death,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Know you not ſuch unrighteous ones cannot inherit the Kingdom of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. Neither ſhall the fleſhly Bodies of the Saints inherit the Kingdom of God till a change hath paſſed upon them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 50. the following words give the Apoſtle's meaning, <hi>Neither ſhall Corruption inherit Incorruption,</hi> v. 51. this Change muſt be. <hi>For</hi> ver. 53. <hi>this Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion muſt put on Incorruption, and this Mortal muſt put on Immortality.</hi> V. 54. <hi>Then will be brought to paſs the ſaying, Death is ſwallowed up in Victory. Hoſea</hi> 13. 14. Moreover, it appears that Chriſt roſe from the dead, and aſcended in his Body of Fleſh, Blood and Bones. <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 39. he ſaid to his Diſciples, <hi>Feel me and handle me: a Spirit bath not Fleſh and Bones, as you ſee me have; and he ſhewed them his Hands and his Feet,</hi> that were nailed to the Croſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Even ſo will <hi>he change our vile Bodies, and make them like unto his own glorious Body,</hi> Phil. 3. 20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> But not to enlarge; I could never yet underſtand by any of your Writings, that you own any other Reſurrection than the new Birth, or Regeneration. I ſhall cite two or three of your Authors: <hi>Smith's Catechiſm,</hi> p. 29. <q>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> But muſt Men paſs through Death, and riſe again in this Life, or whilſt in this Body? <hi>Anſwer,</hi> Yes; <hi>for except he be regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated and born again, he cannot enter the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God:</hi> and therefore he muſt die to the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:192303:43"/>
firſt <hi>Adam</hi>'s Fleſh, and be quickened and riſe again in the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi>'s Spirit; and ſo in the Reſurrection and Life enter the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> See <hi>James Nailor</hi>'s Book, <hi>Love to the Loſt,</hi> p. 3. <q>Whereby, ſaith he, the Heart is freed from Corruption, and made able to eſcape the Pollutions of the World, and to run in the pure ways with delight, which is the glorious Liberty of the Sons of God, the Reſurrection from the Dead.</q> Add to this the Skill that <hi>S. Fiſher</hi> uſeth to make null this Article of the Chriſtian Faith, in his <hi>Velata qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dam Revelata:</hi> Thus, <q>But if you will not be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed, nor perſwaded by <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets within you, neither will ye be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded by ſuch of us, who were once dead in Sin with you, but are now riſen to Life by the Power of God, which is his Light, and in the ſame ſent to ſpeak to you from the Dead.</q> The Text he ſeems to allude to, is, <hi>Luke</hi> 16. 31. but what an horrid Abuſe this is to the words of our Lord, and the Scope and Deſign of them, the Chriſtian Reader will eaſily ſee. But from what hath been ſaid by theſe your Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and I might enumerate many more of like import; thus much may be farily concluded, That you believe no other Reſurrection but only Regeneration, or a new Birth. I own that Regeneration is ſet forth in Scripture under the terms of a Death, Burial and Reſurrection, according to <hi>Rom. 6. 2, 3, 4. Col.</hi> 3. 1,—4. and <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 12, 13. But doth it follow, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe here is a Death to Sin ſpoken of, and a
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:192303:43"/>
being <hi>buried with Chriſt by Baptiſm, and a riſing again to newneſs of Life; having put off the old Man, with his Deeds,</hi> &amp;c. that therefore we are to believe no other Death, Burial, or Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection? The two former are ſelf-evident, and within the reach of Senſe; it is the third, namely, the Reſurrection of the Body from the Grave of the Earth, that you ſtumble at and oppoſe, even as the Sadduces did, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. 23. But <hi>ver.</hi> 29. Chriſt gives them an Anſwer, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Ye do err, not knowing the Scriptures, nor the Power of God:</hi> and <hi>ver.</hi> 31, 32. he proves this Doctrine to them from what God ſaid, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3. 6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly;</hi> It appears you do not only deny the Reſurrection of the Body from the Grave of the Earth; but the eternal Judgment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Judgment-Seat of Chriſt, at the laſt Day, you concluding it to be paſt already: Elſe what doth your Friend <hi>Lawſon</hi> intend in his fore-mentioned Book, <hi>pag.</hi> 9, and 19. who affirmeth, <q>he hath eternal Life in Poſſeſſion, and is now in the Poſſeſſion of the Kingdom?</q> And what elſe means your Friend <hi>Desbury</hi> in his Book called, <hi>A Diſcovery of Man's Return to his firſt Eſtate?</hi> p. 7. he ſaith, <q>The Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is paſt already as to us, as having, ſaith he, given an account to God already for all that we have done, and received the Reward for our Sins, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> And this may be if what was ſaid in your Book, called, <hi>Saul</hi>'s <hi>Errand to Damaſcus,</hi> were true, That <hi>George Fox</hi> was the eternal Judg of Quick and Dead; ſo that there
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:192303:44"/>
was no occaſion for you to mention either of theſe Points of the Chriſtian Faith, for in your proper ſenſe you believe neither. But I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand why you abuſe the World in your Paper in ſaying, You believe, hope or expect Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, Juſtification and Salvation when your Belief is, you have them already, and are in the Reſurrection, and in the eternal Kingdom of God already. I count it impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for me to ſay, I expect what I really have; nay, it's not only improper, but falſe; and as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 24. <hi>That which is ſeen is not Hope,</hi> &amp;c. Now from all this, tho I could have added many more Inſtances from their own Tongues and Pens, had occaſion been, I ſhall lay before the Reader the ſad Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of their Unbelief in theſe two Points of the Chriſtian Faith.</p>
            <p>And it tends to eat out and deſtroy the very Life and Vitals of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>1. If our Bodies ſhall not riſe from the Grave, then Chriſt is not riſen, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 13. this is clear in the Text; and <hi>ver. 16. If the dead riſe not, then is not Chriſt raiſed:</hi> ver. 20. <hi>But now is Chriſt riſen,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo certainly ſhall the Reſurrection of our Bodies be.</p>
            <p>That Chriſt did ariſe from the dead, <hi>&amp;c. 1 Cor.</hi> 15. 5, 6, 7, 8. above five hundred are Witneſſes to this Truth.</p>
            <p>2. If the Dead riſe not, then Preaching is vain, and Faith is vain, and the five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Witneſſes, with the twelve Apoſtles, are all found falſe Witneſſes. <hi>Revelat. 1. 18. I
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:192303:44"/>
am he that was dead, and am alive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. If the Reſurrection of the Dead, or riſing again, or ſtanding again, be not a Truth; (for ſo the Greek and Latin words ſignify) then the Prophecies of the Prophets, and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of the Apoſtles are falſe, <hi>Iſa. 26. 19. Thy dead Men ſhall live, together with my dead Body ſhall they ariſe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and the Earth ſhall caſt out her dead. Dan. 12. 2. Hoſea 13. 14. Acts</hi> 24. 15. That there ſhall be a Reſurrection of the Dead, both of the Juſt and Unjuſt. Muſt the Juſt be regenerated? <hi>Acts 26. 8. Why ſhould it be thought a thing incredible, that God ſhould raiſe the Dead?</hi> It cannot be meant of Regeneration, or the new Man riſing in the old, as you ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſay; for that was never thought incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible by the <hi>Sadduces, Epicures</hi> or <hi>Stoicks,</hi> nor by the Heathen Philoſophers nether, all did own that God, or the Gods, could make Men better, and turn them from Vice to Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. If our dead Bodies ſhall not riſe from the Grave, then the Hope of the Primitive Saints was all vain, null and void. <hi>John 11. 24. I know,</hi> ſaith <hi>Martha, he ſhall riſe again at the Reſurrection at the laſt Day. Heb.</hi> 11. it is ſaid of thoſe famous Believers, that they all <hi>died in the Faith, not having received the Promiſe,</hi> &amp;c. Phil. 3. 20. <hi>We look for the Saviour, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: who ſhall change our vile Bodies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I told one of your Friends, <hi>J. W.</hi> that I looked for Chriſt's ſecond, perſonal and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:192303:45"/>
Coming. He told me I may look till my Eyes fail'd.</p>
            <p>5. If the Dead riſe not, then the beſt Saints are the moſt miſerable Men in the World, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15, 19, 30, 32. it's but vain to ſtand in Jeopar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy every hour, or to fight with Beaſts, yea, to undergo any Sufferings for Chriſt, if the Dead riſe not: And know this, it is not the Sufferings, but the Cauſe for which, that makes the Martyr. But if the Dead riſe not, there is no Cauſe for Sufferings at all: but we may <hi>eat and drink, for to morrow we ſhall die.</hi> The licentious Atheiſt is the moſt happy Man, ſince no Glory or future Reward in another World is to be expected.</p>
            <p>So that as thoſe Primitive Hereticks, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 18. <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Pheletus,</hi> who, by ſaying <hi>the Reſurrection was paſt already, had overthrown the Faith of ſome;</hi> ſo would you. Chriſt died and roſe again to deſtroy the Power of the Grave; but by this Hereſy, the Grave muſt deſtroy our Bodies for ever: which God forbid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly;</hi> How can you conclude you are in the glorious Kingdom, and that you have Eternal Life now really in Poſſeſſion?</p>
            <p>1. For our Lord ſaith, <hi>In the Reſurrection they neither marry, nor are given in Marriage, Mat.</hi> 22. 30. <hi>Luke</hi> 20. 35. Now this you do; therefore not in the Reſurrection, nor that Kingdom.</p>
            <p>2. In that Kingdom they can die no more: but that you do as other Men; <hi>Revel.</hi> 21. 4.
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:192303:45"/>
no more Death, Crying, nor Sorrow, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but this you have; therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. In that Kingdom no Hungering, or Thirſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: but theſe you feel and experience here; therefore not in the Reſurrection, nor that Kingdom.</p>
            <p>4. No more Sickneſs nor Pains: but all theſe you have here. O then fool not your ſelves with ſuch falſe Dreams! but believe Chriſt will ſhortly come in Glory, and every Eye ſhall ſee him. And conſider what a ſad Surpriſe it will be to you when the Trumpet ſounds, the Graves are opened, and your Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies raiſed to ſtand in Judgment! But let all faithful Chriſtians ſay, <hi>Come, Lord Jeſus, come quickly.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THere is preparing for the Preſs a ſhort, but profitable Diſcourſe, entituled, <hi>The Trial and Condemnation of Whiſpering Backbiter,</hi> deſigned as a means to detect the Sin of Detraction; an Evil too common, not only amongſt the Profane, but Profeſſors of this Age.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By <hi>E. P.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:192303:46"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:192303:46"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
